<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact diary of the late expedition of His Illustrious Highness, the Prince of Orange, now King of Great Britain, from his palace at the Hagve, to his landing at Torbay, and from thence to his arrival at White-Hall giving a particular account of all that happened, and every day's march / by a minister, chaplain in the army.</title>
            <author>Whittel, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 160 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65950</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W2044</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4013</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11791913</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11791913</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49238</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65950)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49238)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ;556:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact diary of the late expedition of His Illustrious Highness, the Prince of Orange, now King of Great Britain, from his palace at the Hagve, to his landing at Torbay, and from thence to his arrival at White-Hall giving a particular account of all that happened, and every day's march / by a minister, chaplain in the army.</title>
                  <author>Whittel, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 75 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Richard Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Whittel. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>William --  III, --  King of England, 1650-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Revolution of 1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Exact DIARY OF THE Late Expedition OF <hi>His Illuſtrious Highneſs</hi> THE <hi>Prince of Orange,</hi> (Now KING of <hi>Great Britain</hi>) From his Palace at the <hi>HAG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E,</hi> To his Landing at <hi>TORBAY;</hi> And from thence To his Arrival at <hi>WHITE-HALL.</hi> Giving a particular ACCOUNT Of all that happened, and every Day's March.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By a Miniſter, Chaplain in the ARMY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Richard Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> M DC LXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:2"/>
            <p>Licenſ'd,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>April</hi> 23. 1689.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>JA. FRASER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:3"/>
            <p>AN Exact Diary of the late Expedition OF HIS ILLUSTRIOUS HIGHNESS THE Prince of Orange, INTO ENGLAND.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:4"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE, <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> Earl of <hi>Bedford; WILLIAM,</hi> Earl of <hi>Portland; HENRY,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Sidney</hi> of <hi>Sheppy,</hi> AND Sir <hi>JOHN MAYNARD,</hi> One of the Lords Commiſſioners of the GREAT SEAL.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORDS,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHen I ſeriouſly reflect upon the ſtupendious Providence of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, in bringing to paſs the late and unpreſidented Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> now King of <hi>Great Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:49238:5"/> I cannot do leſs than Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate thoſe Noble Perſons, that both favour'd and joyn'd in ſo good a Work, among whom your Honours had a conſiderable ſhare, which made me prefume to lay this ſhort <hi>Compendium</hi> of that Expedition at your Feet, hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly craving your candid Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and Patronage of it, (tho' not varniſh'd with quaintneſs of Phraſe, or Elegancy of Wit and Rhetorick, but in a lame and plain Stile). Your Honours are not inſenſible how near we were to Ruine, nor how his Sacred Majeſty King <hi>WILLIAM,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded all that was dear, for our good, which ſhould oblige the moſt ungrateful to make ſome anſwerable returns of Gratitude and Loyalty. Your Honours have
<pb facs="tcp:49238:5"/> fully convinced the World of your uprightneſs and ſteadineſs in this Cauſe. All that I can ſay cannot add to, but will rather de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract from your Honours innate Worth and Goodneſs I heartily wiſh this good Work, ſo far alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy advanced, may be fully com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleated, ſo that we may have no reaſon to fear a relapſe. And that the God of Heaven may preſerve our gracious King and Queen, and proſper their good Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions with ſuitable ſucceſs, and convert all their Enemies, or make them fall before them, is the daily Prayers of,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Honours,</salute>
               <signed>your Honours most Humble and most Obedient Servant, JOHN WHITTLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:49238:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49238:6"/>
            <head>AN Exact Diary of the late Expedition OF HIS ILLUSTRIOUS HIGHNESS THE Prince of Orange, (Now KING of <hi>Great Britain)</hi>
            </head>
            <p>HIS Illuſtrious Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who is of a truth another <hi>Joſhua,</hi> in his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daunted Spirit and Magnanimity for the Lord's Cauſe, and proſperous Conduct of his People <hi>Iſrael:</hi> Another good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> in doing that which is right in the ſight of God, deſtroying Idolatry while he was yet young: Another <hi>David,</hi> or <hi>man after God's own heart,</hi> and a zealous Defender of that Faith which is tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ancient, Catholick, and Apoſtolical; receiving an account of the exceeding great Cruelty and Barbarity of <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks in <hi>France,</hi> towards all them that profeſſed the true Reform'd Religion, or the Proteſtant Faith in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; and that indeed without any regard to the Hoary head, (thô found in the way of Righteouſneſs, which is a Crown of Honour) without any reſpect to Sex, or poor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Babes, which could not diſcern between their right and left hands: and not only hearing of their unheard-of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:49238:7"/> Cruelty, but even beholding daily at the Court, and about his own Sacred Perſon, not a few who had ſometime been the Objects of their Direfulneſs, and undergone, to their great ſorrow, their Barbarity: among many others, a pious aged Miniſter of the Goſpel, whom (for adhering to the Truth, and holding faſt the profeſſion of his Faith, without wavering) theſe Sons of <hi>Belial</hi> took and bound faſt unto a large Spit, and turn'd him as a Pig at a great Fire, after a direful manner, until he was near half roaſted alive, inſomuch that his Eyes were almoſt ready to drop out of his Head, his Bloud in the Veins much dried, his Sinews not a little ſcorch'd, and the poor man a meer Cripple at this very day, as may be ſeen by the curious Inquiſitors; althô God who is faithful, did not ſuffer him to be tempted above what he enabled him to bear, and in his appointed time made a way for him to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape their cruel Hands, ſo much embrued in the Bloud of the Saints, and in the Bloud of the Martyrs of Jeſus. And beſides this Miniſter, many of both Sexes, who had been tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by their cruel Hands: Men, who had been bound faſt with Cords, while their own Wives were moſt immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtly uſed and entreated, and then aſſaſſinated before their ſorrowful eyes: Women who had been violently held, while the tender Bowels of their own dear Husbands were ript out even before their faces running down with tears; and the ſucking Infant cruelly murdered in the arms of its Mother that bear it, to the breaking of many womens hearts. Nay, ſo exceeding great was the Cruelty and Barbarity of theſe Bloud-thirſty Papiſts towards the Proteſtants there, that no Pen is able to delineate it, or any Tongue expreſs it, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry few <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts capable of conceiving it, our Nation (God be praiſed) being unacquainted with ſuch abominable Practices.</p>
            <p>Now, as was ſaid, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hearing and behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their curſed Facts, was exceedingly concern'd for <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> becauſe he had a real love for her; and therefore this good <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s heart did even melt within him, and he har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49238:7"/> and ſuccour'd very many of theſe poor and deplorable Proteſtants, who were under ſo ſore a Tryal. How did he long to have theſe Sons of Satan vanquiſht, and the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> rebuilt! and therefore did not count his own Life dear to him, that he might cauſe the true Spouſe of Chriſt to reſt ſecurely. And verily we may hope that <hi>Babylon</hi>'s fall draws near, and that the Kings of the Earth, who have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted Fornication with her, ſhall partake of her Miſery, and ſee her Plagues come in one day, <hi>Death, and Mourning, and Famine.</hi> Without doubt, thoſe many thouſands of Souls un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Altar, which were ſlain for the Word of God, and for the Teſtimony which they held, do cry continually with a loud voice, ſaying, <hi>How long, O Lord, holy and true, doſt thou not judge and avenge our bloud on them that dwell on the earth? Nebuchadnezzar</hi> the Great, may, before ſeven times paſs o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver him, be driven to confeſs, ſaying, <hi>As I have done to the Saints, ſo God hath requited me; and the ſame meaſure that my cruel People meaſured to the Proteſtants in my Land, is now meeted to my Popiſh Realm.</hi> But for us of this Kingdom and Nation, we may well rejoyce in God that made us, in God that redeem'd us, in God that ſanctified us and all his Elect; in God who hath ſo lately delivered us out of the hands of our implacable Enemies, when we were as Sheep appointed to the ſlaughter: We ought to extol him that rideth upon the Heavens, by his Name <hi>Jah,</hi> and rejoyce before him. And well may our Nation be right joyful in our King and Queen, by whom <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is made a Praiſe in the Earth, and who are (in truth) as good, as God hath made them great; and modeſtly and juſtly as far excel all others in Virtue and true Piety, as they are above them in Sphere or Station.</p>
            <p>Now his Illuſtrious Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Enemies of the Lord had broken down the Walls of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and raz'd them even to the ground in <hi>France,</hi> becauſe the publick and ſolemn Worſhip of God in Spirit and in Truth, is not to be found in any part of that Kingdom now: And ſeeing that thoſe Engines of Satan were at work in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49238:8"/> Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> (Kingdoms unto which this great Prince had ſuch a Right and Title, not only by Affinity or Marriage of her Royal Highneſs, his moſt entirely beloved Conſort, but alſo by Conſanguinity or Birth, his Royal Mother, deceaſed, being Daughter to K. <hi>Charles</hi> I. of bleſſed Memory) for ſuch was the Arrogance and Haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſs of all Papiſts now in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> but eſpecially of the Jeſuits and Prieſts, that they conſulted how to deſtroy the Proteſtants, and extirpate the Lord's In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, that they ſhould be no more a People here, and that their Name ſhould be rooted out: Nay, ſo far had they proceeded in this Diabolical Deſign, that even the Popiſh Kings of the Earth begun now to ſet themſelves, and the Rulers took counſel together againſt the Lord, and againſt his Anointed, and the purchaſe of his Bloud: therefore now they began to ſay of our <hi>Sion</hi> here, <hi>Down with it, down with it, raze it to the ground, and ſuffer not ſo much as one Heretical Branch to remain.</hi> But he that ſitteth in the Heavens, did laugh; the Lord had them in deriſion: for he knew well their Fall was at hand, and that the Righteous ſhould have cauſe to rejoyce. Nay, as if 'twere not enough for theſe Prieſts and Jeſuits to inſult over mens Bodies, they pretend Authority over mens Souls, and frequently would ruſh into what Houſe they liſted, in a very impudent manner, and moleſt the dying perſon with their deſtructive and pernicious Diſcourſes, torment poor Souls departing this life, and where they could, they forc'd the Breaden or Wafer-God to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. And which was no ſmall aggravation to our miſery, or addition to our ſorrow, no part of our Nation was now free from theſe Ravening Wolves, which went about in Sheeps cloathing. Theſe Serpents had now crept into every little hole or creek about the Land. And all this came to paſs by the great encouragement and protection of the late K. <hi>James</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary;</hi> perſons, every man can tell, that made it their principal buſineſs to abet and protect the Prieſts and Jeſuits, enlarge the Kingdom of Antichriſt, and promote the Intereſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:49238:8"/> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the great Harlot and Mother of all Abomination and Wickedneſs: therefore without all controverſie, their minds were blinded by the God of this World, becauſe of their unbelief, leſt the light of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, who is the Image of God, ſhould ſhine unto them: Hence they were wholly given over to a reprobate mind, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve Lyes and Fables, and Traditions of men, before the pure Word of God, and more ſure Word of Propheſie, which is Truth, as Chriſt himſelf teſtifies: Therefore they mightily encouraged the Evil, and diſcouraged the Good; abetted and protected them who ſaid the Bible was falſe; <hi>(as Father</hi> Peters <hi>his Brother publickly preacht againſt our Bible, averring there was ſeveral hundred Faults and Contradictions in it,</hi> &amp;c.) but ſuſpended and diſanimated our Reverend, Pious, and Learned Clergy, who did not walk in Craftineſs, nor handle the Word of God deceitfully, but by manifeſtation of the Truth, commended themſelves to every man's Conſcience in the ſight of God: for the Doctrine taught and maintain'd in our Church, is ſound and uncorrupt, and grounded purely on the ſacred Scriptures. Take but a glimpſe of the irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Zeal of the late K. <hi>James,</hi> to promote the Mother-Church, when he ſaid to Father <hi>Peters,</hi> in his Chamber, (who ſoon communicated it unto thoſe at <hi>Antwerp, Keulen,</hi> and <hi>Liege,</hi> of his own Society, and commended his great and fervent Zeal) <hi>I had much rather reign but one year to an end, and then die a Martyr, with the Converſion of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>to the</hi> Roman <hi>Faith, than reign thirty years pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperouſly, and leave them at my death in Hereſie as I found them when I came to the Crown.</hi> And I preſume we may gueſs rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily what would have been our Lot, and was intended for us, had not the Lord God Omnipotent ſhew'd himſelf <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him</hi> in our behalf, and remembred us when we were in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, by that ſaying of the late Q. <hi>Mary</hi> unto the Pope's Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio, <hi>I hope to dine all the Hereticks in the Kingdom, by ſuch a day</hi> (naming the day) <hi>for one Half-crown:</hi> for even now they <hi>know not what to do,</hi> and are at their Wits end. God is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49238:9"/> ſtronger than Men; and greater is the Spirit that is in the Children of God, than the Spirit that is in the World: for when they concluded the Day was their own, then were they on the top of the Precipice, and all their evil Devices ſoon confounded. Was it then any wonder at all, to have our ancient <hi>Engliſh</hi> Laws ſacrificed, our Rights, Liberties, and Priviledges deſtroyed, our ancient Charters wreſted from us by violence of a <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> our Colledgians at <hi>Oxford</hi> turn'd out by a ſuperſtitious <hi>Mandamus,</hi> and a Crew of Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures placed therein? The Law of God in effect made void, and Popiſh Legends ſet up in the place; when the late K. <hi>James</hi> and Q. <hi>Mary</hi> were fed with corrupt and unſound Food; nay, when they abetted and protected thoſe who taught them Doctrines of Devils: for ſuch is the Doctrine taught and maintain'd in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in theſe days, if we may credit St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, inſtead of the ſincere Milk of the Word of God, and wholſome Food of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures? What could our Nation expect from the hands of Bloud-thirſty Papiſts, and eſpecially <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (had they not been prevented by the goodneſs of God, and the unparallel'd Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution of the Prince of <hi>Orange)</hi> but Fire and Faggot, Wrack and Gibbet, when many of them judg'd that to be the only way for to merit the Kingdom of Heaven, by breaking Faith with Hereticks, and deſtroying them in ſuch a manner? How many pious Lords and virtuous good men have loſt their lives by the Papiſts Subtilty and Juggles, thô pretenſively by Law, when unrighteous Popiſh Judges tryed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned them, who had no fear of God before their eyes, and whom the righteous Judge will accuſe (no doubt) at the day of Judgment? But there is one ſtep higher to aſcend, and then we have done: What was likely to befal us, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed Idols, and burnt the Groves, and ſometime ſince drove out the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> when one of that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on did reign over us? and one that thought himſelf cloathed with a Deſpotick and Arbitrary Power, exerciſing the ſame in <hi>Scotland,</hi> beginning here to do the like? And hence he
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49238:9"/> told our Right Reverend Biſhops, when they waited on him about the reading of his illegal Declaration in the Churches, <hi>I will make you to know, that I am your King, and that I muſt, nay, I will be obeyed; be it at your peril.</hi> Althô this command was contrary to the holy Word of God, the Canons of our Church, and the ancient Laws and Statutes of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, therefore our Right Reverend Biſhops were hurried into the <hi>Tower.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, when the Prieſts and Jeſuits ſaw plainly, that they could not poſſibly get ſuch a Parliament, which would eaſe them of the Teſt and Penal Laws, thoſe two intolerable Yoaks, (as they forſooth called them) thô the late K. <hi>James</hi> himſelf, and all the Romaniſts within our Land, had done their very uttermoſt, uſing corrupt and unlawful means, in order thereunto: Then they thought to force us to take away the Teſt and Penal Laws, therefore the late K. <hi>James</hi> ſent out <hi>Mandamus</hi> after <hi>Mandamus,</hi> but our brave <hi>Engliſh</hi> hearts would not be driven, thô they might be won, therefore they refuſed his <hi>Mandamus,</hi> becauſe it was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to Law, Cuſtom, and Priviledge. Then he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Declaration to be read in every Church by the Miniſter, after Divine Service, and before Sermon; and this not taking effect, they knew not what to do, for very few read his Declaration, except ſome double minded men about our Church, which are unſtable in all their ways. Now thoſe Soul-deceivers about the Court, advis'd the late K. <hi>James</hi> for to ſend unto <hi>Holland,</hi> and try the inclination of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the Princeſs, and deſire their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent concerning the taking off the Teſt and Penal Laws, which accordingly was done by his Envoy, M. <hi>D' Abbeville.</hi> But theſe two, being like <hi>Zacharias</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous before God, and walking in all the Commandments and Ordinances of the Lord blamleſs, not only refuſed to grant their royal Aſſent hereunto, but even ſign'd their Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of ſuch a wicked Fact, as appears apparently by the Lord <hi>Fagel</hi>'s defence of himſelf, againſt ſome implacable
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49238:10"/> Papiſts in our Kingdom: For which deed they immediately ſet themſelves on work againſt the very beſt of Princes, and broached the late Queens being with Child, and it would certainly be a Prince of <hi>Wales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the All-ſeeing Eye, being upon them, ſoon brought to light their hidden work of darkneſs, and raiſed up a good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> to break the power of Idolatry here: For his illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orance,</hi> by his moſt accurate eye, and with his profound ſagacity, ſoon eſpy'd the Popiſh Myſtery of Iniquity, which was ſo gloſs'd over with equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation, prevarication, and mental reſervation; and ſaw very plain thrô all the miſts of their Roman and Italian Shams, and thrô the clouds of their ſpecious Pretences, the inevitable ruin and deſtruction of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> if that this ſuſpected Child was not timely prevented: Nay, he ſaw in the bottom of this Plot, by the Sons of the Kingdom of Darkneſs, the total Subverſion of the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Church of Chriſt; therefore he judged it high time, for the Lord's peculiar People, now to ſtand up for his Cauſe, for the defence of his Truth and Goſpel, to reſiſt the Devil and all his Imps, now our necks being under oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by Popiſh Governours, our Inheritance turn'd to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, and our Houſes to Aliens, (I mean unto theſe Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceivers) wherewith our Nation did ſwarm: For the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits and Prieſts of <hi>Baal</hi> Anti-chriſt, did now feed on the beſt of the Flock, and devour the Fruit of our Land, while many able Miniſters of the Goſpel had ſcarce Bread left for to put in their mouths, (I mean thoſe that were ſuſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Biſhop of <hi>Durham)</hi> inſomuch that the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants hang'd down their Heads like a Bulruſh, and were not a little concerned to ſee the partial proceedings of the Court; and being unable for to bear any longer their moſt unjuſt and abominable Actions, it pleaſed our heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo to rule and guide the Hearts and Minds of the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Gentry, and ſome others of our Land, that they join'd together, and with one accord, earneſtly invited and deſired
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49238:10"/> his moſt illuſtrious Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> (as being the only Perſon under Heaven capable of doing it) for to give himſelf the trouble and charge of coming over with an Army here, to deliver our Land and Nation out of the hands of all thoſe implacable and blood-thirſty Enemies, who long'd now to deſtroy us, as alſo to free us from a Deſpotick and Arbitrary Power. Therefore the renown'd Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> who was ever forward to hazard his own Perſon, and venture his Life for the Life of the Goſpel, to preſerve and maintain the Truth and Purity of it, againſt all ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and oppoſers, did not delay anſwering their earneſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation, nor defer fulfilling their cordial Deſires. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he conſulted with the High and Mighty Lords, the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>West-Friezland,</hi> aſſembled now at the <hi>Hague,</hi> concerning this great Work, and the moſt proper Methods to be uſed by him, that the glorious deliverance of our Nation (thrô the bleſſing of Almighty God upon his Endeavours) might effectually be wrought: And the firſt ſtep thereunto was, to make choice of fit Inſtruments, becauſe God works in theſe days by Means (Miracles being long ſince ceaſed.) Hence he commands all the Dutch For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces for to Muſter and Encamp about <hi>Nimeghen,</hi> not very far from the <hi>Brandenburghers</hi> Camp (the famous Duke of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> being alli'd unto his illuſtrious Highneſs): The Regiments being all incamp'd, according to his Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Order, he was pleaſed to view them one by one, and make choice of the very flower of the Army, to ſerve him in this glorious Expedition. He thought it very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to carry over into <hi>England</hi> ſuch a Force with him as might (thrô God's aſſiſtance, and the Proteſtants concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence) make the enemies of the Lord to flee before him, and drive out all the Prieſts of <hi>Baal,</hi> and cleanſe <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> of Idolatry, as good <hi>Joſiah</hi> did; for now the Altars of <hi>Baal</hi> were ſet up by thoſe curſed Vipers, in moſt places of our Realm, as divers were ſet up in our Metropolitan City of <hi>London,</hi> (that renown'd ancient Proteſtant City)
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49238:11"/> to the exceeding great ſorrow of our Reverend Clergy, and diſcouragement of our holy Reform'd Church. Having now made choice of what Officers and Soldiers he thought moſt fit here, he went unto the great Duke of <hi>Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi>'s Camp, and made choice of what Regiments he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed there, for to take with him into <hi>England;</hi> and then, with all the ſpeed that might be, he return'd to the <hi>Hague.</hi> It's certain, that very many people thought he took too much trouble upon him, to ride thus from one City to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nay to fly, as ſome expreſs'd it, becauſe he made ſuch haſte; and all was for to deliver the true Reform'd Church of Chriſt out of all her enemies hands, and to make the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God enjoy reſt and peace, that every man might ſit peaceably under his own Vine, and drink the Wine out of his own Ciſtern. Therefore order was ſent unto every City in <hi>Holland,</hi> for to make clean their Men of War, and fit them out for Sea, with all ſpeed, that they might be mann'd, victuall'd, ſtored with Powder and Ball, and all ſorts of Utenſils for War, and be ready to ſerve his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in his glorious deſign, for the good of the Proteſtant Churches of Chriſt, but eſpecially thoſe in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> Now, according to the Order, every City very willingly, and indeed with more than an ordinary cheerfulneſs, ſet their men to work and rigg their Ships, paying them double Wages, that they might labour day and night, until it was done, becauſe they now ſhewed their zeal, and did ſtrive which ſhould be ſooneſt prepared with their Veſſels, for to go out to Sea, and ſerve his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> From <hi>Amſterdam</hi> were fifteen good Veſſels well rigg'd, and every thing in compleat or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, ſet out to Sea the firſt Wind that ſerv'd, becauſe every Wind will not bring them out of the <hi>Texel;</hi> it muſt be an Eaſterly Wind, or elſe they are block'd up, and they would not be hindred or backwards now for never ſo much, ſo they rode at anchor in the Sea. And from the City of <hi>Rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdam, Dort, Delph, Leyden, Harlem,</hi> and all other Cities,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49238:11"/> were many Veſſels fitted out to Sea, according to each City's proportion in War, and their wonted Cuſtom, which Ships join'd the other Ships from <hi>Amſterdam.</hi> Then in <hi>Zealand</hi> a conſiderable number of brave Veſſels were ſet out, with all things neceſſary for War: As from <hi>Middleburgh, Vliſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſingen, Vere, Tertol,</hi> &amp;c. and theſe ſail'd to the <hi>Hollands</hi> Men of War, and joined them riding at anchor; ſo the Fleet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to compleat: Now the Navy rode at anchor about ſome two or three Leagues from the <hi>Brill,</hi> and there remain'd ſome days.</p>
            <p>It's worthy of any man's obſervation, to conſider what an univerſal conſent there was unto this glorious Underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and Expedition of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> for the wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> for this conſent and accord was not only generally among the high and mighty Lords, the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Friezland,</hi> but even among all ſorts and conditions of men, there was not one perſon in the Land heard to murmur, or ſpeak the leaſt word againſt it, (Papiſts only excepted) but all with one accord and one mind and heart, endeavoured to forward and expedite this glorious Undertaking; nay, the very Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, Maidens, and Children, were lifting up their Prayers unto the God of Heaven, for to bleſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and crown his deſigns in hand, for the good of the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd Church with ſucceſs, according to the deſire of his own heart: which thing I duly obſerv'd, and therefore was ſomewhat confirm'd in my opinion concerning this great Work in hand, which cauſed me to declare publickly, That the great Jehovah, or living and true God, had not only put it into the heart of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> a Prince whom he had raiſed up to advance his Glory, and the Intereſt of his Church and People, and therefore made him ſo ſtrong for himſelf, ſo great a terrour to the evil, as well as praiſe to thoſe that do well; but that the Lord had alſo ſtirr'd up the hearts of all his people, to join together as one man: and hereupon I could not but judge, that God had a delight in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49238:12"/> this Work, and would certainly bring it to paſs in his due time, not when our ſilly fancies urg'd it: And made it now my work to endeavour for to keep our people that they did not tempt God, or limit the holy One of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> of a truth, the Reverend Clergy of the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> are not to be forgotten, becauſe they did wreſtle with God in their Prayers, in the great Congregations and Solemn Aſſemblies, after a moſt ſervent manner, with Sighs and Tears, in the behalf of our Churches, in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> and mightily encouraged all the Soldiers, to ſhew their cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage for the Cauſe of God, againſt the Children of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and Enemies of his Church and peculiar People. So that they have obliged our Nation (as the Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> in his Sermon at <hi>Exeter</hi>-Cathedral ſaid) to be kind to the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> for ſundry weighty Reaſons, and, amongſt others, their kindneſs to us, and towards our Land, in this happy Expedition. The Men of War were riding at anchor in the forementioned place, waiting for his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Orders, what to do, or where to go; ſundry hundred of Merchants Ships, Pinks, Fly-boats, and others, were hired for this Service, and many immediately ſent to the Fleet; others went for Men here and there, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as they receiv'd order; ſome were to carry Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, others to carry Horſes; ſome Hay, others Artillery, or Ammunition, and all ſorts of Neceſſaries convenient for the War: Many Martſcutes and flat-bottom'd Boats, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the River only, to tranſport Goods and People from City to City, were hired now to tranſport the Soldiers from <hi>Nimighen</hi> unto the Men of War and Merchant-Ships, Pinks and Fly-boats, riding at anchor, ready to receive them, or any thing that was order'd them to receive by our great Maſter. I ſhall not retard the candid and ingenuous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with an ample Diſcourſe concerning the manner of their coming down the <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Moſe,</hi> or <hi>Maze;</hi> how the Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghers, at every City, with their Wives, Children, and whole Houſhold, came crouding unto the great Head,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:49238:12"/> which is without the Ports towards the River, a place made purpoſely for convenience of taking in, or ſhipping off Goods, or for commodious lading, or unlading Veſſels; and took their ſolemn leave, moſt Praying, and ſome Cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for them. The Soldiers were ſome of them playing on the Hoeboys, <hi>Dutch</hi> Flute, and other Inſtruments; others were beating the Drums, and ſome ſounding their Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, which I muſt confeſs made no diſcord in the harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, as they were ſailing down the River. There are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers pleaſant Cities upon the <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Moſe,</hi> between <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighen</hi> and the <hi>Brill,</hi> as all thoſe who have travell'd in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> know very well: Being come unto the Fleet, all the Soldiers were preſently ſet on board, ſome to the Men of War, ſome to the Merchant-Ships, ſome to the Pinks, and ſome to the Fly-boats: And the Schippers, with their Martſcutes and flat-bottom'd Boats, return'd home. The Wind was now Northerly, or North-Weſt, which is the very worſt Wind that can blow for the Coaſts of <hi>Holland;</hi> and the Weather waxed daily worſe and worſe, the Winds growing ſtronger and ſtronger, inſomuch that the Seas grew very rough, the Waves ſwell'd, and lifted their proud tops towards the Clouds, and the poor ſmaller-Ships were ready to be overwhelm'd, ſhaking their Heads, as if they would ſhake their Sails off; and being unable for to endure ſuch Weather long, (ſo far in the Sea as they now did ride at anchor) without very great hazard and danger, his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was inform'd thereof, who ſuddenly gave order for all the ſmaller Veſſels to come into Habour. The Men of War weighed their Anchors, and ſail'd to a far more ſafe and commodious place for anchorage, in caſe of a Storm, for every man ſaw the Weather was unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the Air very troubleſom.</p>
            <p>The ſecond place where they rode at Anchor, was between <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Zeeland,</hi> about two or three leagues from the ſhore or coaſt: In this place they did ride at Anchor certain days; but while they were here the Weather grew ſtormy,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49238:13"/> and one night the Winds were ſo very high, and the Air ſo tempeſtuous and ſtormy, ſhaking the very Houſes and Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in their Beds, inſomuch that many judged it to be a Earthquake; the whole Fleet was in great peril: and after this, various falſe Reports were ſpread all over the <hi>Nether<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands;</hi> without all doubt broach'd by the Enemies to this Expedition, who trumpetted it about for to amuſe the vulgar People, <hi>That the Anchors and Cables of the Men of War were broken in the Storm, as if they had been a needleful of Thread, ſo that all the Ships were driven here and there, ſome to one ſhore, and ſome on another Coaſt, and as yet they were not heard of.</hi> Which Fables did ſtartle the poor ignorant ſort, and they knew not what to judge or ſay: others who were more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, and underſtood better the <hi>Holland</hi> manner of Ships, and the Art of Navigation, ſoon made anſwer to this Sham of the Papiſts, <hi>That there was no queſtion (by the bleſſing of God) but that the Men of War were all well and ſafe, becauſe they were able to ride the Storm out, having good new Anchors and Cables; and if any Anchor or Cable ſhould happen to break, theſe Ships could live well enough in the greateſt Tempeſt, provided they have but ſufficient Sea-room.</hi> And ſuch was God's good providence, that all the Ships receiv'd very little or no dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, only a certain old Fire-Ship, which was ſoon chang'd for another, (that being ſent to be mended). The common thing every morning, which was moſt us'd, was firſt to go and ſee how the Wind ſate, and if there were any probability of a change. When any perſon came unto a houſe, in the heart of their City, concerning any manner of buſineſs, the very firſt Queſtion by all was, <hi>Sir, I pray how is the Wind to day? Are we likely to get an Eaſterly Wind ere long? Pray God ſend it,</hi> and ſuch like. The Miniſters themſelves pray'd, That God would be pleas'd for to grant an Eaſt wind. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, a favourable Wind, that might bring his Illuſtrious Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with his whole Fleet (which now attended him) unto the deſired Haven: for nothing could poſſibly be more deſired, than a fair Wind for the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49238:13"/> by all ſorts and conditions of men (except Papiſts). There was a Report here, that the Jeſuits had, promiſed the late K. <hi>James,</hi> that the Weſterly Wind ſhould continue until <hi>Chriſtmas;</hi> but this was falſe, every man knows.</p>
            <p>After ſome time that the Weather had been ſo tempeſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, it began for to ſettle, and God ſent us an Eaſt Wind, to the exceeding great joy of all our hearts in <hi>Holland</hi> and the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> nay, it blew a freſh Gale day by day, and continued favourable that quarter of the Moon; which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed our people to work day and night, that we might be under ſail: The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> order'd every Officer now for to go on board the Ships with their Men, and expedited every thing to the Fleet, with as much ſpeed as men could make; but ſo many things were to be done, it was not poſſible we could be making ſail, ſuch great Bodies always moving very ſlowly, according to the Saying. Some Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giments were expected down the River, and thoſe being come, every thing was ſent to the Fleet, as Proviſion for one month, the Artillery, Magazine, Powder, Ball, Match, Tents, Tent-polls, Stocking-axes, Spades, and all ſorts of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſils convenient in War; and then Hay and Provender for the Horſes, Freſh Water, and a hundred things more, which do not now occur to my memory. The Wind continuing Eaſt, the Horſes began to be ſhipp'd at <hi>Rotterdam,</hi> which was a ſign they were almoſt ready: So his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was pleaſed to take his leave of the High and Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Lords the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Weſt Friezland,</hi> who moſt heartily deſired that God would preſerve him, and bleſs him with Victory over his Enemies, and give him joyful Succeſs in his great Undertaking, for the good of the Proteſtant Church in general, but more eſpecially thoſe in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> The people every-where began to be exceeding ſorrowful for the loſs of ſo Vertuous and ſo Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious a Prince from among them; and very many would weep bitterly at the thoughts of his departure (becauſe all honeſt good men loved him extraordinarily;) and now his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49238:14"/> Health is drank by every Gentleman, and Schipper, Mate, and Boy, and his proſperous Voyage. The Horſes being moſt of ſhipped, the Guards began to come: So upon <hi>Friday</hi>-night all things were ready on board, and the Fleet prepared to ſail, only it waited for the coming of his Highneſs.</p>
            <p>The number of our Capital Ships, or Men of War, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Fifty, which were very well rig'd, mann'd, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with all things requiſite; the number of our Fire-Ships, was about Five and twenty; leſſer Men of War, or Frigats, about Six and twenty; the number of Merchant Ships, Pinks, Flyboats, and others, was about Three hundred and odd: ſo the total number of the Fleet, as they ſailed from the <hi>Brill,</hi> was about Four hundred and odd Ships. But at our ſetting out the ſecond time at <hi>Hellevoot-Sluys,</hi> there were near an hundred Veſſels more, which were <hi>Schievelingers,</hi> or Boats which the Fiſher-men of <hi>Schieveling</hi> went to Sea in, as we ſhall ſhew by and by. But to proceed: The Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi> having taken his Farewel of the States aſſembled at the <hi>Hague,</hi> went unto <hi>Houſlaerdyke,</hi> where he dined with many of his Lords; and after Dinner, on <hi>Saturday, Oct.</hi> 19. old ſtile, <hi>Oct</hi> 29. new ſtile, being unwilling for to loſe this fair Eaſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wind which did blow all the week ſo freſhly, attended with Mareſchal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> Count <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Count <hi>Solms,</hi> the Heer Van <hi>Zuluſtein,</hi> the Heer <hi>Bentink,</hi> the Heer <hi>Overkirk,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Mordant,</hi> the Lord <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> Earl of <hi>Macclesſield,</hi> Earl of <hi>Argyle,</hi> with many other <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch, Dutch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Lords, Knights, and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men; he went in a very rich Yacht unto <hi>Moſeland Sluys:</hi> Her Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> came in another, attended with her Ladies of Honour. Here his Illuſtrious Highneſs took his Farewel of his moſt entirely beloved Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort the Princeſs, who was not a little troubled and grieved for to part with her deareſt Lord and Prince, which cauſed the Tears to diſtil from her precious Eyes like ſo many. Pearls: ſo ſhe return'd with her Maids of Honour unto <hi>Houſlaerdyke</hi> again; but the Prince ſail'd unto the Fleet,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49238:14"/> which made the heart of every man glad, becauſe the wind was ſtill Eaſt: So his Highneſs went on board a Man of War with Admiral <hi>Herbert,</hi> but that Veſſel proving leakie, he ſoon changed, and went on board another. At this time there was very great reſorting unto the <hi>Brill</hi> from every City and Town in <hi>Holland,</hi> for to ſee this glorious, yet formidable Fleet ſet out, but eſpecially to behold his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> committing himſelf unto the mercy of the mercileſs Seas, and the courteſie of the unnatural Waves, ſo freely and willingly, for the ſake of the true Reform'd Churches of Chriſt, but eſpecially thoſe of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi> The top of the <hi>Brill</hi>-Church and Steeple was extreamly throng'd, and the Beam or place made on purpoſe to view Ships, was almoſt broken down with the great crowd upon it; and every man's Eye was unſatisfied with ſeeing, for the more they looked upon the Navie, the more they deſired to look.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs being come on board, every Ship weighed Anchor with all the ſpeed poſſible, and made ſail; the Trumpets ſounded, Hooboys played, and the Souldiers gave a Shout for joy. So when the Spectators perceived that the Fleet was under ſail, they could no longer refrain their Eyes from weeping, nor their Cheeks from running down with affectionate Tears; and many very fervent Prayers were poured for us all, but in an eſpecial manner for the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> When we were ſail'd ſo far that they could not ſee us well any longer, then they made uſe of Perſpective-Glaſſes, and ſent their hearts and well wiſhes with us, and ſo each departed to his own Habitation.</p>
            <p>Thus was our Great Prince croſſing the proud Waves with all his Fleet round him, enjoying a very favourable Wind for <hi>England,</hi> (if it had but continued ſo for ſome days together.) It was about four a Clock in the Afternoon on <hi>Saturday,</hi> when the Fleet firſt weighed their Anchors, and made ſail, upon the coming of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> on board.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49238:15"/> The Evening draw'd on us very faſt, the days being ſhort, and the nights long; ſo when the darkneſs ſeized us, and night was ſhutting upon us, every Veſſel ſet up a Light in the Lanthorn: The Men of War ſet up two, and the Ship wherein the Prince was, had three for a mark or diſtinction. After night, the Wind began to ariſe high, and the Seas wax'd rough, the Waves began to roar and ſwell, lifting up their head aloft, and many now began to ſuſpect the Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as well they might: for within a while the Winds turn'd and blew a very dreadful Storm, inſomuch that all thought we ſhould never ſee Land more: for there were ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry circumſtances which did add to the peril of the Storm, as many skilful Mariners ſaid, The darkneſs of the night, the matter of Carriage, Horſes; which will rowl from ſide to ſide, if they break their Stays, our Pipes of Water, Barrels of Powder and Ball, and the vaſt number of Ships together, which was worſt of all; for while the Schipper intended to eſcape one on his Starboard, then is he in no ſmall peril of running againſt the other on his Larboard-ſide; nay, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, and before, and all round, there were Ships throwing themſelves from ſide to ſide, after an exceeding fearful man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſo that no Steer-man knew which way to ſteer: The Winds blew, as if they would have blown the very Elements away before them; the Seas raged and foam'd, being all in white forth for anger; the Waves rowl'd one upon the back of another, as ſo many great Mountains; the Ships threw themſelves, and the people in them, from ſide to ſide, and from the fore-part of the Veſſel unto the hinder part, as if they would have beaten themſelves all to pieces; and if it had not been the good providence of the Almighty, we had moſt certainly daſh'd againſt each other, and ſo periſh one by the other. The men of War were better able to live than the reſt, for they did not ſhake themſelves half ſo terribly as the Merchantmen and Pinks, but eſpecially the poor Flyboats; theſe ſtrain'd their Ribs, and hurt their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:49238:15"/> Backs very much, becauſe of their hard lading. The Wind was now North-Weſt, and every Mariner did ſtrive to bear up with that Ship wherein the Prince was, but it was impoſſible for all the ſmaller Veſſels, in ſuch a Tempeſt; there's a huge difference between Ships, one will bear a vaſt Storm, another an ordinary Storm en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangers; nay, many can live in the greateſt Tempeſt, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving but Sea-room enough, when ſome can hardly live in a rough Sea.</p>
            <p>Now the people being thus toſs'd and tumbl'd about the Ship, many wax'd exceeding ſick, and vomitted con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually after a dreadful rate; you could hear the men groan after a pitiful manner; others were ſighing, and not a few praying, and committing their Souls unto God, for they thought their Bodies muſt be Meat for the Fiſh of the Sea. The Sea-men that did belong to each Ship, were almoſt kill'd in working ſo hard for to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve their own and our Lives; but now and then they would refreſh themſelves with a dram of the Brandy-bottle. According as the Sea and the Waves roar'd, ſo moſt Mens Hearts now fail'd them, for fear at the apprehenſion of approaching Deſtruction: A Holy Conſcience (at this time) was a Magazine of Joy, and as good as a thouſand Witneſſes.</p>
            <p>Thus did we tumble and rowl about the Seas, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the unnatural Waves, all this Night. How deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable was the Day-light, which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſays is ſweet! And what a pleaſant thing would it have been, for our Eyes but to behold the Sun, though in the midſt of ſuch a dreadful Storm! A worſe hath not happened for many years, as our ancient Ship-Maſters and Mariners conclude: for Darkneſs adds terrour to terrour, and therefore the fear of death unto many at this time was almoſt as bad as death it ſelf: ſome, <hi>Nabal</hi> like, were dead with fear, and their hearts as a ſtone. Many Ships had their Sails blown
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49238:16"/> off; others had their Maſts broken with the violence of the Storm; the Waves often-times rowling themſelves o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the labouring Ships, ſome had their Main-yards bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; the Pipes of Water often-times burſting open, the Barrels of Powder and Ball ſtav'd; it cannot be conceiv'd what a dreadful thing it was, as alſo what a ſtrange kind of rattling the Bullets running about the Decks, made: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſundry Souldiers cried out, <hi>I am ſure I can feel the Hole where the Sea comes in at;</hi> when (as in truth) it was the Water and Beer together, flaſhing within the Ship; for you muſt know we were moſt of us all in darkneſs, (no Candle being permitted to come under Deck) becauſe of the Magazine.</p>
            <p>After we had made our Supplications for our ſelves, and his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> unto the God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, we ſubmitted our Wills to his bleſſed Will; and I am perſwaded that many now were willing to die, after the thoughts of Death had poſſeſſed their mind ſo long, and been impreſs'd in their memories ſo deeply.</p>
            <p>The Morning-light approaching, we were all much comforted, eſpecially when we ſaw that our Veſſels were whole and ſound, and very little water in her Pump, when it was fathom'd.</p>
            <p>Now we long'd for to hear of our great Maſter, how he did after ſuch a terrible Night, which had befallen us. The Seas continued raging, and the Waves roaring, and exalting their tops as they would touch the Clouds, and we rowl'd about, and could not tell what to do, or which way to ſteer after his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The High and Mighty Lords, the States of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>West-Friezland,</hi> now aſſembled at the <hi>Hague,</hi> thrô their profound ſagacity, and in their great prudence, concluded, that the Fleet muſt needs be diſpers'd and ſcatter'd one Ship from another, and much damag'd by ſuch a terrible ſtormy and tempeſtuous Night as that was, if not deſtroyed in a manner: ſo they
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49238:16"/> on the morrow morning, which was the Lord's day, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the Bow, or Meſſenger, which appertains to them, for to haſten unto the <hi>Brill,</hi> and give order for all the <hi>Loteſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> to go out and cruiſe all the Seas over, between <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> and bring into the Haven of <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> all ſuch Ships as they met with or found. Theſe which they call <hi>Loteſmen,</hi> are moſt skilful Pilots, living at the <hi>Brill,</hi> and bred up to the Sea, being accuſtom'd to ſound all over the Coaſts, that ſo they may know the depth and danger of moſt places: they have Ships made, by the Order of the States, on purpoſe to endure a ſtorm, as indeed they will the greateſt: And therefore by Nine or Ten of the Clock, there were not a few of theſe <hi>Loteſmen</hi> cruſing up and down the Sea, and all the Ships which they found, they order'd for to go into <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> ſeeing the Winds ſo ſtormy, and and the Seas ſo very tempeſtuous, return'd unto the <hi>Holland</hi> Coaſts, and came into the Haven of <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> with a conſiderable number of Men of War and Merchant-men, Pinks and Fly-boats; and many Men of War more could have come into the Haven, but ſtaid out on purpoſe to ſecure the Fleet. When we and other Ships had heard, that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was ſafe in the Harbour, we gave thanks to God, and were not a little joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful at this good News, and made towards <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> as faſt as we could: Many Veſſels in this ſtorm were driven near the Coaſts of <hi>England,</hi> others towards the North, ſome into the <hi>Texel,</hi> and others into <hi>Zeeland,</hi> and every day they came into the Haven from one place or other. The <hi>Loteſmen</hi> did no ſmall ſervice to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and the States, in giving Ships information where to go; for many having no Orders, knew not what to do, whether they ſhould make for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſts, or return back to the Coaſts of <hi>Holland.</hi> All thoſe Ships which were any way damag'd in the ſtorm, were now order'd to be repair'd here; ſo that the Smiths, Ship-Carpenters, and others, were forc'd
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49238:17"/> to work day and night, becauſe they ſhould be ready to go out again the firſt Wind that ſerv'd, for his Highneſs was fully reſolv'd, by the bleſſing of God, for to ſet to Sea a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as ſoon as all the Ships were come in and made ready.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Loteſmen,</hi> having cruſed ſundry days up and down the Seas, between <hi>Holland, England,</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> inform'd his Highneſs, that they could not hear of any Ships loſt, thô driven far away, and ſafe in one Habour or another, excepting one Fly-boat laden with Men and Horſes, which, having loſt her Rudder in the violence of the ſtorm, was driven upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Coaſts, and ſo taken by the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh,</hi> the Men being made priſoners, and the Horſes ſent to the late K. <hi>James.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The taking of this Veſſel (we heard) made no little noiſe amongſt the Papiſts in <hi>England,</hi> but eſpecially among the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tories.</p>
            <p>But, to return, this <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys</hi> is a ſmall Haven, or Harbour, for the <hi>Dutch</hi> Ships, wherein they keep ſome of their Men of War, and build new Veſſels, as well as repair old ones: Here they keep a good part of their Magazine and Artillery; and at <hi>Delph, Amſterdam,</hi> and other places, there is much more. Now this place, or <hi>Dorp,</hi> being ſo very ſmall, and every man that could being ſo exceeding wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to get to ſhoar, after our being ſo long tumbled and toſs'd on the Seas, in ſuch a fearful Storm and Tempeſt, was exceedingly throng'd, every Houſe in the <hi>Dorp</hi> being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely crouded, inſomuch that Proviſion grew exceeding ſcarce, and Lodgings could hardly be gotten for Money; thoſe that were gotten, being exceſſive dear: indeed the people of this place made it their Fair, but I muſt condemn them, for impoſing and exacting on us all, in ſuch a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, after we had been ſo fateagu'd at Sea; certain honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable perſons were conſtrain'd for to ſeek Lodgings after Night, and in the Rain, their Servants trying every Houſe,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49238:17"/> inſomuch that ſome worthy Gentlemen reſolv'd for to ſit up, and let theſe noble perſons have their Beds; others gave a <hi>Duccatoon</hi> for ſitting up by the Fire all Night; and not a few being deſtitute of Lodgings, were forc'd to go into the Villages thereabout: Proviſions, after ſome days, were not to be gotten, and that little which was there, was very dear; therefore many travell'd into the Countrey, and bought their Proviſion at a Boors Houſe, that is to ſay, a Countrey-mans Houſe. The Weather was tempeſtuous, and the Seas continued very raging, however Ships came in daily, but people that were on ſhoar could not get back to their Ships, riding now at anchor in the ſtream before <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> the Boatſmen durſt not adventure to carry them in thoſe little Boats, for ſome had been caſt away, coming to ſhoar. The Horſes were taken out of the Ships, and ſent here and there unto the Boors houſes for to be kept, in order to recover them well again, and a very great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was taken out of the Ships dead, and many died after they were ſet on ſhoar; others were bruiſed after a wretched manner, ſo more Horſes were ſent for from <hi>William-Stadt,</hi> and other places, by the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> It was order'd here, That the <hi>Dutch</hi> ſhould begin their Prayers in the Church every Morning at Nine of the Clock, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at Ten, and the <hi>French</hi> at Eleven: The <hi>Dutch</hi> begin their Prayers in the Afternoon at Two, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> at Three, and the <hi>French</hi> at Four of the Clock; which Order was pun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually obſerv'd ſo long as we were here. The Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now Biſhop of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> read the Prayers of of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> according to the <hi>Rubrick,</hi> and dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly paraphras'd upon one or two of the <hi>Pſalms</hi> for the day. The <hi>Dutch</hi> they preach'd, having divers Chaplains to the Regiments appointed them. The <hi>French</hi> ſometimes had a Sermon, but generally Prayers. Upon Sunday, <hi>October 28. Old Stile,</hi> the Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> preach'd in the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Prince being there, with Mareſchal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49238:18"/> all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch</hi> Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen: His Sermon was very pathetical, and very preſſing unto a holy life and converſation, putting all in remembrance of the great peril we were in, ſo lately at Sea; and of the holy Vows and Covenants, which (ſays he) no doubt moſt of you did then make to God; and therefore he deſired, that we would not forget our ſelves any more; and told us all in expreſs words, That if we were not truly reform'd in our lives and converſations, that we ſhould not be thought worthy to be inſtruments of ſo glorious a Work, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the Lord, as he had begun, would bring it to paſs, not by us, but ſome others, who were more ſincere in his Service, and in the due obſervation of his Laws.</p>
            <p>The Air was extreme tempeſtuous, and the Weather very ſtormy. At this very day, when I go to my Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, methinks I ſee that moſt pious and exemplary Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> before my face; how very earneſt he was with the Lord, in his Prayers here, upon his bended knees, after a moſt devout manner, cauſing publick Prayer to be made in the Houſe where he lodged twice a day; he was an Example and Preſident unto all about him, how duly they ought to remember their Creator.</p>
            <p>The Weather continuing very ſtormy and tempeſtuous, and little or no probability of a change or alteration, the People of this place proceeding ſtill to exact on us all; ſome of our Lords (whether <hi>Dutch</hi> or <hi>Engliſh,</hi> it matters not) were pleaſed to inform his Highneſs thereof; who preſently ſent to the States about it: Therefore a poſitive Order came forth in print, what we muſt pay, and no more; ſo much a night for Lodging, ſo much a pound for Cheeſe, Butter, Bief, Mutton, Veal, Bacon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo many Eggs for a <hi>Styver,</hi> and ſo much to ſit up by the Fire, Eighteen <hi>Styvers</hi> for one Night, having a freſh pair of Sheets, and lodging there no more, but if he continued,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49238:18"/> Six <hi>Styvers</hi> a Night; Four <hi>Styvers</hi> for to ſit up by the Fire, Ten <hi>Styvers</hi> a Pound of Butter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Divers Lords came to viſit his Highneſs after the Storm, and her Royal Highneſs came in her Yacht unto the <hi>Brill,</hi> where his Highneſs met her, with many <hi>Engliſh, Dutch,</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Nobles, Knights, and Gentlemen; and having dined to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, they parted each from the other, the Prince re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning in the Evening unto his Fleet at <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> and her Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi>Orance</hi> unto <hi>Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaerdyke.</hi> People came daily from all parts of <hi>Holland</hi> to viſit their Friends, and very many <hi>Dutch</hi>-women to vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit their Husbands; but moſt went to the <hi>Brill</hi> for Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion and Lodging: the <hi>Brill</hi> is about ſome four or five <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles from this place.</p>
            <p>Being noiſed abroad, that we were at <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> and that all ſorts of Proviſions were ſo exceſſive dear, the People came thronging with their Boats, and all things within a while was at a very reaſonable rate. Here we heard, that the Prieſts and Jeſuits, with the Papiſts at <hi>Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp,</hi> in the <hi>Spaniſh Netherlands,</hi> ſung <hi>Te Deum</hi> in their Churches, becauſe the <hi>Hereticks</hi> were caſt away, with their great Conductor, and made uſe of <hi>Moſes</hi> Song. when as we were daily rendring our hearty Praiſes and Thankſgivings unto the Lord our God, for his ſtupen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious deliverance of our whole Fleet out of ſuch a ſtorm, and all the Churches in the <hi>Netherlands</hi> did the ſame.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was not in the leaſt diſmay'd in all the Storm, when moſt mens hearts were as ſtones, dead with fear, his Countenance was obſerv'd not to alter, as other mens did, but, like a true <hi>Paul,</hi> or ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, he encouraged all in the Ship where he was, making them cheerful, when their Spirits were dejected, ſaying to ſome in the Ship theſe words, or to this effect, (as I received information from one in the ſame Veſſel) <hi>For my own part, I am not in the leaſt doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:49238:19"/> but that we ſhall do very well; I know God is a righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous God, and trys the very hearts and reins, and ſees the very end and bottom of my thoughts: He knows my inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity in this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, that 'tis not to get my ſelf a name, or for my own ſake, but for the promotion of his Glory, and his Churches good; and therefore he will not give his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies any cauſe to rejoyce in the deſtruction of the pure in heart.</hi> Our Horſes dying daily were thrown over-board, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very perſon now begins to think of ſetting out again: all the Ships are revictuall'd with a Month's Proviſion more, beſides the old Store which was left; ſo that every Ship muſt needs have overmuch, rather than too little: And, thô people may ſpeak their pleaſure concerning <hi>Holland,</hi> how they feed on Hèrbs and Fiſh altogether, I am ſure, there were ſundry Barrels of good Beef and Pork, with ſufficient Cheeſe and Butter, as could be eaten, on board every Ship.</p>
            <p>Order was now given unto all the <hi>Schievelingers</hi> for to come to the Fleet at <hi>Hellevoot-ſluys,</hi> and accompany us to <hi>England,</hi> for to ſet the Horſes and Soldiers on ſhoar, with all expedition, which the ſmall Ship-boats could not do. And according as they receiv'd order, ſo they came, and ſail'd about from one Ship to another.</p>
            <p>While we were here riding at anchor, (for we tarried here about eleven days) there was a certain Miniſter went unto the <hi>Brill,</hi> to purchaſe ſome things he wanted, to take along with him in the Ship for to eat, and a Papiſt ſeeing him in a Shop, and hearing him ſpeak to the people about the Storm, (whether or no he was a Prieſt he could not ſay) in a taunting impudent manner began thus: <hi>Now, Sir, I ſuppoſe the Courage of you all is well cool'd, and you are convinc'd, that the Lord was much offended and angry, with the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>and his whole Fleet, for this raſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertaking, and therefore he made the Wind and the Seas to reſist them, and take his Churches part, and it</hi>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:49238:19"/> 
               <hi>may be a warning unto every one of you, that you do not fight against God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Unto which this Divine ſoon made anſwer, ſaying, <hi>Alas, you are very much miſtaken, and far from the truth, for by theſe external Providences and Diſpenſations of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, no man can judge aright of his love or hatred, becauſe himſelf tells us plainly, that God maketh his Sun to riſe on the evil and on the good, and ſendeth rain on the just and unjust: St.</hi> Paul's <hi>Shipwreck was no argument God was angry with him; nor was that a ſign, that he was a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer, becauſe the Viper hang'd on his hand, altho' the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſorious fooliſh</hi> Barbarians <hi>judged ſo in like manner. This Storm coming when our Fleet was at Sea, is no argument that God was offended with the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>or this Navy, for he is a conſuming fire, when he is provoked. And hence we may certainly conclude, that it was to prove us, not to deſtroy us; for 'tis apparent to the World, that we are not conſum'd: Therefore as the</hi> Barbarians <hi>chang'd their ſpeech, when they ſaw</hi> Paul <hi>ſhake off the venomous Beast into the fire, without receiving any harm, ſo may you and all your blinded people, learn to judge better, ſeeing our vast Fleet hath been out in ſuch a terrible Storm and Tempest, without ſo much as one Ship lost or cast away. This was to give an ample demonſtration to the whole World of the power of God, and let all men ſee he could preſerve his own children in the greatest of Storms: This was to exerciſe our Faith and Patience; and bleſſed be his holy Name for it, that we are living Monuments of his praiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All people, in the <hi>Netherlands,</hi> were now imploring the Lord, for to grant us an Eaſterly, or favourable Wind, which might bring the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and his Fleet, unto the long deſired Haven, that ſo the enemies of the Lord might be found lyars, and that the Jaw-bones of thoſe Soul-deceivers might be broken in their mouths: And the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49238:20"/> whole Fleet being once more in a readineſs, long'd to be under ſail; ſo much about <hi>Octob. 30. Old Stile,</hi> and <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb. 9. New Stile,</hi> the Wind turn'd about, and came full Eaſt, and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> hearing thereof, and ſeeing the Wind blow ſo freſh, was fully reſolv'd (by the bleſſing of God) to ſet to Sea on the Morrow, not to loſe any time, and therefore every Ship took care to have all things in a readineſs, inſomuch that many were forc'd to work hard all Night, to get Water and other things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient on board, for they had heard, that his Highneſs was reſolv'd to tarry for nothing, and therefore he would leave all behind, which were not ready.</p>
            <p>So upon <hi>Thurſday, Novemb. 1. Old Stile, Novemb. 11. New Stile,</hi> after the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had din'd with all <hi>Engliſh, Dutch, Scotch</hi> and <hi>French</hi> Lords, Knights and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men attending his Sacred Perſon, about three or four of Clock in the Afternoon he went on board a new Veſſel of about Twenty eight Guns with the <hi>Rotterdam</hi>'s Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, call'd the <hi>Brill,</hi> as ſome will have it, and being now in his Cabin, fired, for to give notice unto all the Fleet, to weigh their Anchors, and make Sail, which was accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly done by every Ship, with all poſſible expedition. The whole Fleet was divided into three Squadrons; the Red Flag was for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Scotch,</hi> commanded by Major-General <hi>Mackay;</hi> the White Flag was for the Prince's Guards, and the <hi>Brandenburghers,</hi> commanded by Count <hi>Solms;</hi> the Blew Flag was for the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> commanded by Count <hi>Naſſau.</hi> Now every Ship had a certain Mark, or Token, that it might be known unto what Squadron ſhe belong'd.</p>
            <p>So once more the whole Fleet (thrô God's bleſſing) was under ſail for <hi>England,</hi> with a very favourable Eaſt Wind. The darkneſs coming on us, all the Ships ſet out their Lights, which was very pleaſant to ſee, and the Ship
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49238:20"/> in which the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was, had three Lanthorns, the Men of War two, and each other Ship one. The Tower of <hi>Gowre</hi> Steeple was ſeen a great way in the night, becauſe of the Fire burning thereon.</p>
            <p>Now the Winds were very proſperous, the Seas very calm, and the Waves very humble, and by the Compaſs we all pointed towards the North; ſo that many conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for certain we ſhould land ſomewhere there. It was generally ſuppoſed, that the Scouts which came to watch us from the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet, ſeeing we all made Northward, haſtened to acquaint the Lord <hi>Dartmouth</hi> thereof; and after ſome hours ſailing in the night, the whole Fleet ſtrake ſail, and was driven by the Waves.</p>
            <p>On the Morrow-morning <hi>Friday, November</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, old ſtile, the Men of War fled about the Fleet, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſing the ſcattered Ships for to ſecure them, and keeping all the ſmall Veſſels under their protection; and by that time all the Ships were come within a reaſonable compaſs, it was about ten or eleven of the Clock; and then every Veſſel made ſail, and ploughed through the Waves with all ſpeed towards the <hi>Engliſh Coast.</hi> We ſaw none ſave only our own Ships. It was a very good Wind as could blow, and withal a brisk gale.</p>
            <p>When the Evening was come, we all ſtrake ſail, and were driven of the Waves all night, as we had done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. This driving was not very pleaſant, the Veſſels having no ſail, would throw themſelves from ſide to ſide, and all the people in them, after a ſad ſort; ſo that this put us in mind of the Storm: however, there was no peril in this, though 'twas a little trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
            <p>Many of the <hi>Schievéling</hi> little Veſſels, which came out with us, were loſt on the way in the night; I do not mean caſt away, but broken off from our Ships;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:49238:21"/> they were made faſt with Ropes to each Merchantman, and the toſſing of the Waves, and rowling of the Ships, ſoon brake the Rope, if not prevented in time.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Saturday</hi> morning, <hi>November</hi> the third, old ſtile, as ſoon as the Sun-beams had diſſipated the Miſt, and diſpers'd the Fogg, we could diſcover Land very eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; about which men did vary: ſome judging it to be in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> others in <hi>Kent,</hi> (as it was.) So the Men of War flew round us all, as before.</p>
            <p>Now it happen'd that two of our Pinks were driven out from us a vaſt way, as far as ever we could ſee, and making all the ſail the Veſſels could bear for to come up to the Fleet, they were eſpied by the Men of War, who judging theſe two Ships to be two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Frigats, or <hi>French</hi> Capers, becauſe they made all the ſail they could.</p>
            <p>Our Men of War making ſail, haſtened to ſee what they were. It would have made a Coward magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, for to ſee how the Men of War fled proudly over the Seas; and within one quarter of an hour they had ſurrounded theſe two ſmall Veſſels, and finding them to be of our Society, they preſently return'd, each departing from the other.</p>
            <p>The Wind continued very favourable, and withal blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a good freſh Gale, we made all the ſail each Ship could bear, and now pointed towards the Channel. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout mid-day we were entring between <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Calis:</hi> Here our Great Maſter tack'd about for to ſee the Reer well come up; for many Ships will not make ſpeed, or ſail ſwiftly, with never ſo much ſail: It was a very clear and pleaſant day, as heart could deſire.</p>
            <p>The Reer coming up, we all made ſail again, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened towards the Weſt of <hi>England;</hi> but between <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Callis</hi> the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> call'd a Council of War,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49238:21"/> and afterwards order'd that his own Standard ſhould be ſet up; whereupon the Men of War ſet out their Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, and ſo did every Veſſel in the Fleet. The Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were all above Deck, for to view the Land on each ſide, and <hi>Dover</hi>-Caſtle; and the whole Fleet was reſolv'd to make a Bravado: ſo each Veſſel kept a due diſtance from the other, and beſpangled the whole Channel with beautiful Ships, and Colours flying.</p>
            <p>Here we made divers Flouriſhes, and no ordinary Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure for the Spectators on the ſhores, it being a Sight worthy of the greateſt Monarch to behold. Sundry Men of War ſailed very near unto <hi>Dover,</hi> and gave the Town and Caſtle ſome Guns; others ſail'd towards <hi>Calis,</hi> and did the ſame.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with three Men of War to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend him, one at a diſtance before his Ship, and one on each ſide, ſail'd forwards before the Navy; and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chantmen, Pinks, and Flyboats ſail'd next, beautifying the Seas, with Officers and Souldiers above Deck. The main Body of our Men of War were in the Rear, for to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe between us and our Enemies, if they had came after us, according as we expected.</p>
            <p>The People both at <hi>Dover</hi> and <hi>Calis</hi> having diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd the Fleet, were amaz'd at ſuch a glorious Sight, yet formidable Navie, inſomuch that all the convenient places for beholding us, were much throng'd, eſpecially in and about <hi>Dover.</hi> One man encourag'd another to come and look upon the Fleet, how the whole Seas were over-ſpread with Ships, and how each Ship was laden with Souldiers. Various was mens opinions concerning the place of our landing; for ſome judg'd in one place, and ſome in another: The Evening approaching, and it growing dark, all our Lights were ſet out, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:49238:22"/>
            <p>Now we could ſee the Fire on ſeveral Towers and pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces as we ſail'd along the Channel towards the Weſt, and many thought that theſe Fires (which were only to direct all ſtrange Ships in the Night) had been Beacons ſet up by the Countrey, according to the Order of the late King <hi>James,</hi> on purpoſe to alarum the Land; when we had ſail'd ſome hours after Night, we all ſtruck ſail, as we had done before; the Weather was very good, and the Wind very favourable, and moſt of our Hearts exceeding<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reviv'd thereby.</p>
            <p>On the Morrow-morning, being the Lord's day, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vemb. 4. Old Stile,</hi> which was the happy Birth-day of his thrice Illuſtrious Highneſs, the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> moſt men were of opinion, that we ſhould land either in the <hi>Iſle of Wight, Portſmouth,</hi> or ſome other convenient place, about which matter they were much miſtaken; for the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> did not ſail, but obſerve the duty of the day; ſo all were driven of the Waves. Prayers and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon being done, he went to Dinner, with ſome Nobles at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending him, and about Four of Clock in the Afternoon made ſail, all the whole Fleet following the example of his Ship; now every Schipper endeavour'd for to keep ſight of the three Lanthorns or Admiral of <hi>Rotterdam</hi>'s Ship, for the ſake of his Highneſs therein. The darkneſs ſhutting upon us, all our Lights were ſet out, as before: It was no ordinary ſight, for to behold the Seas all co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver'd with Lights, the Lanthorns appearing at a diſtance like unto ſo many Stars in the Water, dancing to and fro, here and there, according to the motion of the Ship; but above all, the Cabin of that Veſſel wherein the Prince was, having ſo many Wax Lights burning within it, glit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered moſt gloriouſly, and (at a certain diſtance) being well gilt and varniſhed, it ſeem'd a Paradiſe for pleaſure and delight.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49238:22"/>
            <p>The Wind was very favourable, and we did not drive by the Waves, as we had done every Night before, but made all the Sail that our Ships could bear to keep in ſight of that Veſſel wherein our Conductor was. Many delighted to be above-Deck, it was ſo exceeding pleaſant, between the Stars in the Firmament, and our Stars; the three Lanthorns on the Stern, ſhining with Wax Lights, dazled our Eyes, and was the only Compaſs by which moſt of the Fleet ſail'd this whole Night: The Wind blowed very freſh, which cauſed our whole Fleet to plow the curling Waves, and croſs the appeaſed Seas, with very good ſpeed and pleaſure; and towards the morning all ſtruck Sail, excepting thoſe in the Rear, which endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to come up to us as faſt as they could. So when the day began to dawn, we found that we were very near the Engliſh Shore, but whereabout we could not yet tell; The Ship in which the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was, ſailed ſo near the Shore, that with much facility a Man might caſt a Stone on the Land; we were driven very ſlowly, all our Sails being ſtruck: The Morning was very obſcure with the Fog and Miſt, and withal it was ſo calm, that the Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels now as 'twere touch'd each other; every Ship coming as near unto the Ship wherein the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was, as the Schipper thereof would permit them. Here we were moving for a while very ſlowly by the Shore, and could ſee all the Rocks thereabouts very plain. We per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that we ſhould land thereabout, but no place near was commodious for either Men or Horſes, it being a ſteep Rock to march up. The Ships did all obſerve the motion of the three Lanthorns, which were driven by the Coaſt of <hi>England</hi> back again, for we had ſailed ſomewhat beyond <hi>Torbay:</hi> And being thus calm'd for a while, it af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards pleaſed the God of Heaven, that he gave us a Weſt, or weſterly Wind, which was the only Wind that could blow to bring us ſafe into the Bay; for even
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49238:23"/> to this place we had an Eaſt and South-Eaſt Wind, which was indeed a good Wind to bring us from <hi>Holland,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long all the Channel, but not to carry us into the Bay, there were ſo many Rocks and Shelves on that ſide. Making ſome Sail again, his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> gave order that his Standard ſhould be put up; and accordingly it was done, the White Flag being put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>permoſt, ſignifying his moſt gracious offer of Peace unto all ſuch as would live peaceably: And under that the Red or bloody Flag was ſet up, ſignifying War unto all ſuch as did oppoſe his juſt Deſigns. The Sun recovering ſtrength, ſoon diſſipated the Fog, and diſpers'd the Miſt, inſomuch that it prov'd a very pleaſant Day: Now every Veſſel ſet out its Colours, which made a very pleaſant ſhew. By this time the People of <hi>Devonſhire</hi> thereabout had diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered the Fleet, the one telling the other thereof; they came flocking in droves to the ſide or brow of the Hills to view us: Some gueſs'd we were <hi>French,</hi> becauſe they ſaw divers white Flags; but the Standard of the Prince, the Motto of which was, <hi>For the Proteſtant Religion and Liberty,</hi> ſoon undeceived them.</p>
            <p>Others more diſcreet ſaid, that it was the <hi>Dutch</hi> Fleet ſo much talk'd of in the Nation, and ſo long expected by moſt People. This Day was very remarkable in <hi>England</hi> before, being the fifth of <hi>November,</hi> the Bells were ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as we were ſailing towards the Bay, and as we landed, which many judged to be a good Omen: before we came into the Bays-mouth, as we were near the Rocks, the People ran from Place to Place after us; and we being ſo near as to ſee and diſcern the Habit of the Country Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they able to ſee us and hear our Voices; a certain Miniſter in the Fleet, on board the Ship called the <hi>Golden Sun,</hi> went up to the top of the uppermoſt Cabin, where the Colours hang out, a Place where he could eaſily behold all the People on the Shore, and where they might moſt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49238:23"/> perfectly ſee him, and pulling a Bible out of his Pocket, he opened it, and held it ſo in his right Hand, making many flouriſhes with it unto the People, whoſe Eyes were fix'd on him, and duly obſerv'd him; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſignifying to the People the flouriſhing of the Holy Goſpel, (by God's Bleſſing upon the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Endeavours) and calling out as loud as he was able, faid unto them on the top of the Rock; <hi>For the Proteſtant Religion, and maintaining of the Goſpel in the Truth and Purity thereof, are we all by the Goodneſs and Providence of God come hither, after ſo many Storms and Tempeſts: Moreover,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>It is the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>that's come, a zealous Defender of that Faith which is truly Ancient, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick, and Apoſtolical, who is the Supream Governonr of this very great and formidable Fleet.</hi> Whereupon all the People ſhouted for Joy, and <hi>Huzza's</hi> did now eccho into the Air, many amongſt them throwing up their Hats, and all making Signs with their Hands. So after the Miniſter had given them ſome Salutations, and they returned him the ſame again, he came down from off the upper Deck, unto the vulgar one among his Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, who ſpoke to him about the People on the brow or ſide of the Mountain.</p>
            <p>'Tis, methinks, impoſſible for any Man to be ſo blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as not to diſcern the Finger of God in this Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, from the beginning to the end thereof; for a very favourable Wind now fill'd our Sails, and brought us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the long-deſired Haven, to the Joy of our Hearts, and comfort of <hi>England,</hi> and that the Wind ſhould turn a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout from Eaſt to Weſt, when we came to the very place where we were to tack about, is not to be forgotten: It is in effect, as if the living and true God ſhould ſay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> our <hi>Joſhua: As I was with</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, <hi>ſo will I be with thee, I will not fail thee, nor forſake thee: There ſhall not any Man be able to ſtand before thee all the days of thy Life. I have prov'd thee, and thou art
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49238:24"/> not faithleſs: I have weighed thee in the Ballance, and thou art not found wanting. Behold, now will I make the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens to rejoice and ſmile upon thee: Now will I turn the Hearts of this great and ſtrong Nation unto thee; I will bleſs thee with my right and left-hand Bleſſings: Enter there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and poſſeſs this good Land, and be thou Ruler among my People</hi> Iſrael. The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> being come into the middle of the Bay, called <hi>Torbay,</hi> attended with three or four Men of War only, that is to ſay, one or two failing before his Veſſel, and one on each ſide the Ship in which he was; and all the Merchant Ships, Pinks and Fly-boats coming round him, as near as they durſt for ſafety, the reſt of the Men of War being out in the Rear to ſecure all the little Pinks and Fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boats, and withal to prevent the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Fleet from di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbing us in our Landing: Here we all rode at Anchor for a little while before we landed. At the upper end of <hi>Torbay</hi> there is a fair Houſe belonging to one Mr. <hi>Carey,</hi> a very rigid Papiſt, who entertained a Prieſt in his Houſe: This Prieſt going to recreate himſelf on the Leads, on the top thereof, it being a moſt delightſome day, as he was walking there, he happended to caſt his Eyes towards the Sea, and eſpying the Fleet at a diſtance, withal being pur-blind in his Eyes, as well as blinded by Satan in his Mind, he preſently concludes, that 'twas the <hi>French</hi> Navy (becauſe he ſaw divers white Flags) come to land the Sons of <hi>Belial,</hi> which ſhould cut off the Children of God, or as they call us, the <hi>Hereticks:</hi> And being tranſported with Joy, he haſtned to inform his own Diſciples of the Houſe, and forthwith they ſung <hi>Te Deum.</hi> This was ſecond grand Miſtake, the third time will fall to our Lot to ſing <hi>Te Deum</hi> for our ſafe Landing, (as the Prince had it done at <hi>Exeter</hi> Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dral in the Quire): And becauſe falſe Reports were ſpread abroad, that the People of this Houſe had ſhot ſeveral of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Souldiers, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:49238:24"/> they had burnt down the Houſe: I muſt inform the candid Reader, that there was nothing at all in it, for our People did not give them one reviling word, nor they us; ſome lodged there, while we were at <hi>Torbay.</hi> The major part of the Fleet being come into the Bay, Boats were ordered to carry the Prince on Shore, with his Guards; and paſſing towards the Land, with ſundry Lords, the Admiral of <hi>Rotterdam</hi> gave divers Guns at his Landing; the Boat was held length-ways until he was on Shore: So after he had ſet his Feet on Land, then came all the Lords and Guards, ſome going before his Sacred Perſon, and ſome coming after. There are ſundry little Houſes which belong unto Fiſher-men, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the two Hills, at <hi>Tor-Bay,</hi> where we landed: The People of theſe Houſes came running out at their Doors to ſee this happy Sight. So the Prince, with <hi>Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Schomberg,</hi> and divers Lords, Knights, and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, marched up the Hill, which all the Fleet could ſee over the Houſes, the Colours flying and flouriſhing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Highneſs, the Trumpets ſounding, the Hoit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys played, the Drums beat, and the Lords, Knights, Gentlemen, and Guards, ſhouted; and ſundry <hi>Huzza's</hi> did now eccho in the Fleet, from off the Hill, inſomuch that our very Hearts below on the Water, were even ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed for Joy thereof. On this Hill you could ſee all the Fleet moſt perfectly, and the Men of War ſailing up and down the Seas, to clear them of all Enemies; the Ships in the Rear making all the fail and ſpeed they could.</p>
            <p>The Navy was like a little City, the Maſts appearing like ſo many Spires. The People were like Bees ſwarm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all over the Bay, and now all the <hi>Schievelingers</hi> are ſet to work to carry the Men and Horſes unto Shore with ſpeed, for as yet they had done nothing. The Officers and Souldiers crowded the Boats extreamly, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny being ready to ſink under the Weight; happy was
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:49238:25"/> that Man which could get to Land ſooneſt: And ſuch was the eagerneſs of both Officers and Souldiers, that divers jeoparded their Lives for haſte; ſundry Oars were broken in rowing, becauſe too many laid hands on them; ſome jump'd up to their Knees in Water, and one or two were over Head and Ears. Extraordinary pains was now taken, by all ſorts of Men, to get their neceſſary things to Shore, every one minding his own Concern. The Night was now as the Day for Labour, and all this was done, left the Enemy ſhould come before we were all in a readineſs to receive them. The Country Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was, ringing of Bells for our arrival.</p>
            <p>The Officers and Souldiers were continually march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up the Hill after the manner of the Guards, with their Colours flying and flouriſhing, Hoitboyes playing, Drums beating, and all ſhouting and ecchoing forth <hi>Huzza's.</hi> As ſoon as the Prince had viewed well the Ground upon the top of the Hill, and found the moſt commodious place for all his Army to encamp, he then gave Orders for every thing, and ſo returned down the Hill unto the Fiſhermens little Houſes: One of which he made his Palace at that time, inſtead of thoſe at <hi>Loo, Honſlerdyke,</hi> and the <hi>Hague:</hi> The Horſe Guards and ſome Foot were round about him at other Houſes, and a ſtrong Guard but a little below the Houſe wherein his Highneſs was: All the Lords were quartered up and down at theſe Fiſhermens Houſes, whereof theſe poor Men were glad: Now the Camp began to be fill'd with Officers and Souldiers; for no Officer muſt move from his Company or Poſt. The Foot Guards belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> did encamp within an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſure of plowed Land, about which there was a natural Fence, good Hedges and little Stone Walls, ſo that no Horſe could touch them; Count <hi>Solms</hi> being their Colonel or Commander. Count <hi>Naſſaw</hi>'s Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment encamp'd in another Craft or Incloſure joyning
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:49238:25"/> to that of the Guards, having the like Fence about it as before: The Regiment belonging unto Colonel <hi>Fagell</hi> encamp'd in a Craft or Incloſure next to that of Count <hi>Naſſau,</hi> and ſo all the <hi>Engliſh, Dutch, French</hi> and <hi>Scots</hi> encamp'd according to the aforeſaid manner. The Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were marching into the Camp all hours in the Night; and if any ſtraggled from their Companies, it was no eaſy matter to find them in the dark amongſt ſo many thouſands; ſo that continually ſome or other were loſt and enquiring after their Regiments. It was a cold froſty Night, and the Stars twinkl'd exceedingly; beſides, the Ground was very wet after ſo much Rain and ill Weather; the Souldiers were to ſtand to their Arms the whole Night, at leaſt to be all in a readineſs if any thing ſhould happen, or the Enemy make an Aſſault; and therefore ſundry Souldiers went to fetch ſome old Hedges and cut down green Wood to burn therewith, to make ſome Fire. Now one Regiment beginning, all the reſt ſoon followed their Example: Thoſe that had Proviſion in their Snap-facks (as moſt of the Souldiers had) did broil it at the Fire, and others went into the Villages thereabouts to buy ſome freſh Proviſions for their Officers, being we were newly come from Sea; but alas! here was little Proviſion to be gotten. There was a little Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe amongſt the Fiſhermens Houſes which was ſo extreamly throng'd and crowded, that a Man could not thruſt in his Head, nor get Bread or Ale for Mony. It was a happy time for the Landlord, who ſtrutted about as if indeed he had been a Lord himſelf, becauſe he was honoured with Lords Company.</p>
            <p>On the Morrow after we landed, when all the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers were encamp'd, the Prince with ſundry Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men rode and viewed each Regiment, and then return'd to Dinner at this little Houſe. The Number of his Highneſs's Regiments landed here at this Bay, was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:49238:26"/> ſix and twenty, the number of Officers about one thouſand, the number of Field-Officers about ſeventy eight: The number of all his Forces and Souldiers about fifteen thouſand four hundred and odd Men. You might have ſeen ſeveral hundred Fires all at once in this Encampment, which muſt needs ſignify to the Country round about that we were landed. The Prince here was pleaſed to accept of Peoples Good-Will for the Deed, becauſe things were not here to be bought for Mony, no Market-Town being near. Many People from all the adjacent places came flocking to ſee Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The Horſes were landed with all the ſpeed that might be, and truly were much out of order, and ſore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bruiſed, not able to find their Legs for ſome days: Every thing that was of preſent uſe was poſted to ſhoar, but the Artillery, Magazine, and all ſorts of Baggage and cumberſom things were left on Shipboard and order'd to meet us at <hi>Exeter.</hi> Upon Wedneſday about Noon, Order was given to march towards <hi>Exeter,</hi> and ſo every Souldier was commanded by their Officers to carry ſomething or other beſides his own Arms and Snap-ſack; and this made many murmur exceedingly. Sundry ſcores of Horſes were thrown over-board which died at Sea; ſo that by juſt Computation the Prince loſt about ſix hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Horſe at the leaſt by the Storm. As we marched here upon good Ground, the Souldiers would ſtumble and ſometimes fall, becauſe of a diſſineſs in their Heads after they had been ſo long toſs'd at Sea, the very Ground ſeem'd to rowl up and down for ſome days, according to the manner of the Waves: Therefore it was the Lord's Goodneſs that our Foes did not come upon us in this Juncture and unfit Condition. The whole Army marched all the ſame way in a manner, which made very ill for the Rear Regiments, and caſt them much behind. Many Country People which met us did not know what to ſay or think, being afraid that we ſhould
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:49238:26"/> be ſerved as the D. of <hi>Monmouth</hi>'s handful of Men were. Notwithſtanding, ſome were ſo couragious as to ſpeak out and ſay, truly their Hearts were for us, and went along with us, and pray'd for the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> but they ſaid the <hi>Iriſh</hi> would come and cut them in pieces if it ſhould be known. Some Souldiers asked them if they would go with them againſt the Papiſts? and many anſwered, they were enough themſelves, and wanted no more. His Highneſs, with Mareſchal <hi>Scomberg,</hi> Count <hi>Solms,</hi> Count <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Heer <hi>Benting,</hi> Heer <hi>Zuluſtein,</hi> Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Earl of <hi>Macclesfield,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Mordant,</hi> Lord <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> and divers others Knights and Gentlemen, came in the Rear of the middle Line; for as ſoon as we could conveniently, we were to march in three Lines, and the Prince was commonly or always in the middlemoſt Line, which was the meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt place: So he went unto a certain Gentleman's Houſe about two little Miles off, where the laſt Line encamp'd the ſecond Night, and lodged there, his own Guards being with him. This firſt day we marched ſome hours after Night in the Dark and Rain; the Lanes here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about were very narrow, and not uſed to Wagons, Carts or Coaches, and therefore extream rough and ſtony, which hindred us very much from making any ſpeed: Divers of the Dutch-men being unaccuſtomed to ſuch bad ways and hard marching in the Dirt, wiſh'd themſelves back again in their own Country, and mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mured becauſe of the Dark and Rain: At length we came to the Corn-ſtubble Incloſures on the ſide of a Hill, where we encamp'd that Night: It was a red Clay, and it rain'd very hard the greateſt part of the Night, the Winds being high and ſtormy: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the poor Souldiers being much wearied with the Tent-Polls, ſpare Arms, and other Utenſils for War, which they had carried all Day, and ſome hours after Night, as well as with the badneſs of the March, lay
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:49238:27"/> down to take their Repoſe; and verily the Water run over and under ſome of their Legs the major part of the Night, and their Heads, Backs, and Arms ſunck deep into the Clay, being ſo very wet and ſoft; not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they ſlept all Night very ſweetly in their Pee, or Campagne Coats. The Souldiers here fetch'd ſome old Hedges and Gates to make their Officers and themſelves ſome Fire (as they had done the Night be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) elſe would have periſhed in the Cold, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all over in a Froth with Sweat in marching. And the old Hedges and Gates not being enough, they fetch'd away the new Ones, for the Weather was not only raw and cold, but we our ſelves were ſo too, having nothing to eat or drink, after ſo bad a days Journey: The Souldiers had ſome good <hi>Holland</hi>'s Beef in their Snap-ſacks, which they brought, and their Officers were very glad to get part with them, ſo they broil'd it at the Fire; ſome had bought Chickens by the way, but raw, which they broil'd and eat, as a moſt delicate Diſh. Sundry Captains offer'd any Mony for a Guide to bring them to a Houſe thereabout, where they might have ſome Proviſion for their Mony: but no Guide could be found, it was exceeding dark, and being all Strangers, and unacquainted with the Country, we could not tell where to find one Houſe, for thoſe few that were ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering here and there, were either in ſome little grove of Trees, and ſo hid from our Eyes, or elſe in a bottom amongſt the Hills, and ſo could not be ſeen. Theſe Quarters did not content our Minds, for tho we got as near to the Hedges as we could poſſible with our Fires, yet we could not be warm: Many of the Souldiers ſlept with their Feet in the Ditch, and their Heads on the ſide thereof. We thought this Night almoſt as long as that in the Storm at Sea; and judged it to be the dawn of the Day ſome hours before it was. The Morning appearing, rejoiced our very Hearts, for we thought now we ſhould
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:49238:27"/> march preſently; and we were ſure of this, that worſe Quarters we could never meet with, but much better we hoped to find. A private Souldier therefore going in the next Croft for to ſeek a convenient place, he found it to be an Incloſure with Turnips; ſo bringing his Burden away with him, he came to the Fire, and gave thoſe there ſome, telling his Comrades of the Place, who ſoon haſtned thereto, and brought enow with them: Some roaſted them, and others eat them raw, and made a brave Banquet. The Souldiers were buſy in diſcharging their Muſquets, after the Wet and Rain, for they druſt not truſt to that Charge; and about 11 of the Clock the Army received Orders to march.</p>
            <p>The Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with the Lords Gentlemen, rode from this place unto Sir <hi>William Courtney</hi>'s, within a Mile of <hi>Newton-Abbot,</hi> the firſt Line being about <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and the laſt on their march thither. The Place where we encamped was troden to Dirt, and ſtuck to our Shoes wretchedly. Now the Regiments marched ſundry Roads, of which we were right glad, hoping to meet with better Quarters than the Marl and Clay Crofts. The People came in flocks unto the Croſs-ways to ſee the Army, but eſpecially the Prince. We met with much civility on the Road; now they began to give us Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and pray for our Succeſs: ſundry Perſons enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the Declaration of his Highneſs.</p>
            <p>Now being on their march to <hi>Newton-Abbot,</hi> a certain Divine went before the Army; and finding that 'twas their Market-day, he went unto the Croſs, or Town-Hall; where pulling out the Declaration of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with undaunted Reſolution, he began, with a loud and audible Voice, to read as follows. William Henry, <hi>by the Grace of God, Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>&amp;c. of the Reaſons inducing him to appear in Arms in the Kingdom of</hi> England, <hi>for preſerving of the Proteſtant Religion, and reſtoring the Laws and Liberties of</hi> England, Scotland,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:49238:28"/> 
               <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When the People heard the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Name mentioned, they immediately crowded about him in a prodigious manner to hear him, inſomuch that ſome jeoparded their Lives. The Declaration be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ended, he ſaid, <hi>God bleſs and preſerve the Prince of</hi> Orange: To which the People, with one Heart and Voice, anſwered, <hi>Amen, Amen;</hi> and forthwith ſhouted for Joy, and made the Town ring with their ecchoing <hi>Huzza's.</hi> The Miniſter, <hi>nolens volens,</hi> was carried in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Chamber near the Place; the Windows were ſhut, the Doors lock'd and bolted, to prevent the Crowd from ruſhing in. The People of the Houſe, and others, very kindly asked him; <hi>Sir, What will you be pleaſed to eat? or, What ſhall we provide for you? Name what you love beſt, it ſhall be had.</hi> The Miniſter anſwered, <hi>What you pleaſe, give me what you will.</hi> So they brought forth ſuch as was ready; and having eaten and drunk well, they deſired him to ſpare them but one Declaration. <hi>Yes,</hi> ſays he, <hi>for I have enow in my Pocket;</hi> and pulling them out, he, gave Three, becauſe they were of diſtinct Pariſhes. He told the People, he would go and viſit their Miniſter, and cauſe their Bells to ring, becauſe the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was come into the Pariſh. at Sir <hi>Will. Courtney</hi>'s tho not into the Town; and (ſays he) this being the firſt Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-Town, I cannot but think it much the more proper and expedient. Whereupon he went to the Miniſter's Houſe, and enquiring for him, he was courteouſly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited in, and diſired to ſit down: The Reverend Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Pariſh coming preſently to him, they ſaluted each other; and after ſome; Communications paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, this Divine from the Army, deſired the Keys of his Church-doors, for to welcome the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> into <hi>England</hi> with a Peal, (that being the firſt Market-Town they came to.) The Miniſter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered; <hi>Six, for my own part, I am ready to ſerve his Highneſs any
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:49238:28"/> way, but of my own accord cannot give the Keys; but you know you may command them, or any thing elſe in my Houſe, in the Name of the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>and then I will rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily grant it.</hi> So the Divine ſaid; <hi>Sir, I demand your Keys of the Church Door only for an hour, to give his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs a Peal, and then I will return them ſafely unto you.</hi> The Miniſter preſently directed him to the Clerk's houſe, and deſired him to come and take a Glaſs of Wine with him after the Peal was ended, (but the Ringers coming together, they rung ſundry Peals) and he returned the Keys to the Miniſter. The People of the Town were exceeding joyful, and began to drink the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi>'s Health. The Country People in the Town were well inclin'd towards us; and here was the firſt favour we met with worth mentioning. His Highneſs was moſt kindly receiv'd and entertain'd at Sir <hi>Will. Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney</hi>'s, the Souldiers generally well treated by the Vulgar.</p>
            <p>Now the Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> and another old Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, rode unto <hi>Exeter,</hi> to prepare Quarters for the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The Biſhop's Palace and Deanery be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing both viewed, the Deanery was thought to be the more convenient Place, and ſo concluded upon. The Army moved toward <hi>Exeter,</hi> ſome Regiments being at one Town, and ſome in another: And as they were marching over the Heath, or Common, between <hi>Newton-Abbot</hi> and <hi>Exeter,</hi> about five miles off the City, ſundry Companies of young Men met them, with each a Club in his Hand; and as they approched near, they gave ſundry Shouts and <hi>Huzza's,</hi> ſaying, <hi>God bleſs the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>and grant him victory over all his Enemies; We are his true Servants, and came to fight for him as long as we are able:</hi> So we all bid them welcome. Here the Army paſſed by a Popiſh Lady's Houſe, which was cruel to all her Proteſtant Tenants; ſhe forced ſome to turn Papiſts, or Apoſtates: But had the <hi>French</hi> King's Army paſſed thus by a Proteſtant Houſe, it ſhould ſoon
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:49238:29"/> have been fired, the People put to the Sword, or burnt:But we have not ſo learn'd Chriſt, nor been thus taught by his Miniſters in our Land; for no Man moleſted this Houſe, nor did any viſit it, unleſs a Captain and ſome Gentlemen, which would have bought themſelves Horſes there, having loſt their own at Sea, and ſo conſtrained to walk on foot till they could ſupply themſelves with more.</p>
            <p>It muſt needs be acknowledged by all People, that his Highneſs took ſpecial care in marching of the Army, that no Diſorders ſhould be committed; and never bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Order could be kept in any Army than in this, as all ſorts of Men confeſs: Nay, they told us at <hi>Exeter,</hi> that when we were there, the City was more quiet in the Night, and freer from debauch'd and diſorderly Perſons than 'twas before. The poor Souldiers began now to grow lame, and ſo marched ſlip-ſhod, which was irk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. After the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> had tarried two or three Nights at Sir <hi>Will. Courtney</hi>'s, he, with a brave Train of Nobles, Knights, and Gentlemen to attend him, rode unto <hi>Exeter;</hi> they long'd much for his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. It was a very wet and rainy Day when he came into <hi>Exeter</hi> with his Army. The manner of his coming into this City, being ſo glorious, was long ſince pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, ſo that I ſhall not ſpeak much about it: The Guards rode, ſome before and ſome behind him, with their Swords drawn, their Colours flying, Kettle-Drums beating, and Trumpets ſounding joyfully, their Officers courteouſly bowing unto the People; all ſorts and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Men thronging on each ſide the Streets, making great Acclamations and <hi>Huzza's</hi> as the Prince paſſed by. The Windows of every Houſe were extreamly crowded and beautified; the Bells ringing. The Foot Souldiers did not appear well, becauſe they were ſorely weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beaten, and much dabled in marching in the Dirt and Rain, and look'd very pale and thin after ſuch a hard
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:49238:29"/> days march which made ſome People conjecture that they were dull ſluggiſh Men.</p>
            <p>As the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was riding thus towards the Deanary through the City, attended with Mareſchal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> Count <hi>Solms,</hi> Count <hi>Naſſau;</hi> Heer <hi>Zuluſtein,</hi> Heer <hi>Bentein,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Mac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesfield,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mordant,</hi> Lord <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> Earl of <hi>Argile,</hi> Colonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> Sir <hi>Rowland Guyn,</hi> and divers other Lords, Knights and Gentlemen; Such was the Reſolution and Deſire of an old Woman to ſeé the Prince, that ſhe throng'd in amongſt the Horſe Guards, and tho ſhe was divers times in Jeopardy of her Life, yet for all, ſays ſhe, I will ſee him tho it coſt me my Life: ſo coming at length to him, ſhe touched his Hand and ſaid, I pray God bleſs you, Sir, and ſo was thruſt away by the Guards: but as ſhe was going from him, ſhe put her Hand to her Heart and ſpake out aloud, Now my very Soul within me is the better for ſeeing him; at which Speech and Humour of this Woman, his Highneſs himſelf ſeem'd to ſmile. After the Prince was come unto the Deanary, and had refreſh'd himſelf, with all his Lords and Gentlemen, then was he pleaſed to go and render his hearty Thanks to Almighty God in the Cathedral Church for his ſafe Arrival and the whole Fleet. The People thronged the Streets to ſee him as he went, and crouded the Quire where he was to come very much. Now there were ſundry Men with Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bards who cleared the way, beſides Sentinels: So be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conducted to the Biſhop's Seat, he ſat down, with about ſix of his Life-Guar-dMen on his Right-hand, and many more before him and about him in the Quire. As he came all along the Body of the Church the Organs played very ſweetly, tho 'twas not the right Organiſt himſelf, he being gone aſide on purpoſe, as I was inform'd there. And being ſat, the Quire began and ſung <hi>Te Deum</hi> for the ſafe Arrival of the Prince of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:49238:30"/> 
               <hi>Orange</hi> and his Army in <hi>England</hi> (as alſo for his whole Fleet): After the Collects were ended, the Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> began to read the Declaration of his Highneſs: <hi>William Henry, by the Grace of God, Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>&amp;c. Of the Reaſons inducing him to appear in Arms in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of</hi> England, <hi>for preſerving of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and for the reſtoring the Laws and Liberties of</hi> England, Scotland <hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> At the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of which Declaration the Miniſters of the Church there preſent ruſhed immediately out of their Seats, and buſled through all the Croud going out ofthe Church; the People remained, and were very atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive to the Doctor's reading, and the Declaration being ended, he ſaid, God ſave the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> unto which the major part of the Multitude anſwered, <hi>Amen.</hi> So his Highneſs return'd to the Deanary, the People ecchoing forth <hi>Huzza's</hi> as he went along. Another Evening at Service one of the Miniſters reading that Prayer for the pretended Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> a certain No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble-Man or two being preſent, ſtood up at the ſame and put on their Hats, Kneeling down to all the other Collects; and this they did to demonſtrate their Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of it. The Right Reverend Biſhop of this place and Dioceſs as ſoon as he had learn'd (for certain) that the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was-landed with an Army at <hi>Tor-Bay</hi> in <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> took his Coach and came up to give the late King <hi>James</hi> Information thereof, for which he gave him the Biſhoprick of <hi>York.</hi> The Reverend Dean likewiſe took his Coach and went about ſix or ſeven Miles in the Country, where he remain'd ſome days, but returned unto his own Houſe or Deanary before the Prince came away; for we tarried at <hi>Exeter</hi> many days to refreſh the Army after it had been ſo long on Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and to recover the Horſes to their former Strength, as alſo for the Gentlemen of the Country thereabout to come and joyn his Highneſs there. The Train of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:49238:30"/> Magazine and the whole Baggage of the Army was brought hither by Water; there were one and twenty good Braſs Pieces for the Field, divers of which were too heavy for thoſe Roads, and more than ſixteen Horſes could draw. Arms for ſundry thouſand Men were now given out here, which we brought with us out of <hi>Holland.</hi> The firſt Sunday after the Prince was come unto <hi>Exeter,</hi> being <hi>Novemb.</hi> 11. the Reverend Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> preached before him at the Cathedral Church in the Morning, the Quire and Body thereof being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly throng'd with People which came to ſee his Highneſs, ſome placing themſelves in Seats by eight in the Morning: When his Highneſs came he was pleaſed for to ſit in the Biſhop's Seat in the Body of the Church, as he had done in the Quire before: Sundry Sentinels ſtood juſt behind him, two juſt before him, and many more in the Church-Iſle; the Doctor's Text was <hi>Pſalm 107. 43. Whoſe is wiſe and will obſerve thoſe things, even they ſhall underſtand the loving Kindneſs of the Lord.</hi> The Doctor very accurately ſhewed the loving Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Lord unto the Price of <hi>Orange,</hi> and his Fleet; how he cauſed the Winds to turn at <hi>Tor-Bay,</hi> where the whole Fleet was to tack about to come into the Bay; and then ſhew'd the upright Deſign of the Prince to promote the Glory of God, and good of his Church in <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> having ended his Sermon, he read the Prayer for the Expedition, and ſo concluded with the Bleſſing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Some time was paſſed here before the Gentlemen of the Weſt joyned his Highneſs, but when once they did begin to come in, then they came daily: The Mayor and Aldermen of the City came to viſit the Prince, and were buſie in their Conſultations among themſelves. The late King <hi>James</hi> we heard now was advanc'd as far towards us as <hi>Salisbury,</hi> with a very brave Army, of about thirty five thouſand Men, and a prodigious great Train of Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:49238:31"/> which made the poor Country People tremble. Moreover we heard, that he was fully reſolved to encamp his Army about <hi>Sarum,</hi> in the Plain, where he intended to fight us. Some of our Men, being of the Van-guard, were advanc'd as far as <hi>Wincaunton</hi> to provide Carriage, at which place there was a ſmall Skirmiſh or Action be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 26 of our Souldiers, and about 150 of the late King's Party; which you ſhall have a particular ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of by and by. We ſoon receiv'd information of this Skirmiſh at <hi>Exeter:</hi> Order was now given to get Waggons to carry the Magazine and Baggage of the whole Army, together with all ſorts of Utenſils fit and convenient for War, and Horſes to draw the Artillery, and for the Country People round to bring in their Horſes to be ſold at <hi>Exeter,</hi> that ſo the loſs of our Horſes might be made up here: According to which Order the Country People came daily in with their Horſes to ſell, and the Officers gave great Prices for them, becauſe they muſt have them there or now here: The Souldiers were ordered to keep themſelves and their Arms in good order, and to get every thing here which they wanted. Much Mony was laid out in this City for all ſorts of Commodities which the Officers or Souldiers lacked: Here at firſt the People were ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous about the Dutch Mony, and many Country People refuſed it, but were forc'd to take it, becauſe all the Army had little elſe, but Guineas and Dutch Mony. The People of the City began now to be more and more inclin'd towards our Army, and all fear almoſt of the other Army was baniſh'd out of their Thoughts, ſo that they would diſcourſe more freely now than at the firſt. The Drums beat for Volunteers, and every Regiment of Engliſh or Scotch which wanted any, Men, was now compleated: The Regiment of Sir <hi>John Guyes,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Peyton</hi> fill'd up very faſt; for Men came into the City daily from all Parts to liſt themſelves,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:49238:31"/> inſomuch that many Captains pick'd and choſe their Souldiers: Very great crowding was here at the Dean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary, (it being the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Court) by all ſorts of People: Many coming 20 Miles on purpoſe to ſee him, and all the People of the adjacent Places were waiting there daily; inſomuch that the Sentinels could hardly keep them out. The Guard was before the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the Deanary, and ſundry Sentinels two at each Door. Now his Highneſs received Information, That the late King <hi>James</hi> was gone back from <hi>Sarum</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>London,</hi> (with his whole Army) by reaſon of the falſe Report of ſome Tumult in the City, made by the Apprentices, which News did not in the leaſt diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us. The Weather being ſomewhat favourable, the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with all his Lords and Gentlemen at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending him, was pleaſed to ride and view the City, and Caſtle; and this Day the Deanary was embroider'd with the Officers in their Gold and Silver-Lace Coats. The Country People brought all ſorts of Proviſions in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, becauſe it yielded them Money, and went off well.</p>
            <p>We heard here that our Friends were up in the North of <hi>England,</hi> as the Lord <hi>Delamere,</hi> Earl of <hi>Devonſhire,</hi> Earl of <hi>Stamford,</hi> Earl of <hi>Danby,</hi> Sir <hi>Scroop How;</hi> Sir <hi>William Ruſſel</hi> with divers others: By this time the Gentlemen of <hi>Somerſetſhire</hi> and <hi>Dorſetſhire</hi> were coming in to join his Highneſs; and on Thurſday <hi>November</hi> 15, they waited on him at <hi>Exeter,</hi> upon which he was plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſpeak to them as follows.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tho we know not all your Perſons, yet we have a Catalogue of your Names, and remember the Character of your Worth and Intereſt in your Country. You ſee we are come according to your Invitation and our Promiſe. Our Duty to God obliges us to protect the Proteſtant Religion; and our Love to Mankind, your Liberties and Properties. We expected you that dwelt ſo near the place of our Landing, would have join'd us ſooner, not that it is now too late, nor that we want</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:49238:32"/> 
               <hi>your Military Aſſiſtance ſo much as your Countenance and Preſence, to juſtify our declar'd Pretentions, in order to accompliſh our good and gracious Deſign. Tho we have brought both a good Fleet, and a good Army, to render theſe Kingdoms happy, by reſcuing all Proteſtants from Popery, Slavery, and Arbitrary Power; by reſtoring them to their Rights and Properties eſtabliſhed by Law, and by promoting of Peace and Trade, which is the Soul of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and the very Life-Blood of a Nation; yet we rely more on the Goodneſs of God, and the Juſtice of our Cauſe, than on any Humane Force and Power whatever. Yet ſince God is pleaſed we ſhall make uſe of Humane means, and not expect Miracles for our Preſervation and Happineſs; let us not neglect making uſe of this gracious Opportunity, but with Prudence and Courage put in Execution our ſo honourable Purpoſes. Therefore, Gentlemen, Friends, and Fellow-Proteſtants, we bid you and all your Followers moſt heartily Welcome to our Court and Camp. Let the whole World now judg, if our Pretentions are not Juſt, Generous, Sincere, and above Price, ſince we might have even a Bridg of Gold to Return back; But it is our Principle and Reſolution, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to dye in a Good Cauſe, than live in a Bad one, well knowing that Vertue and True Honour is its own Reward, and the Happineſs of Mankind Our Great and Only Deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The late King <hi>James</hi> coming up towards <hi>London,</hi> the Regiment of Dragoons belonging to the Lord <hi>Cornbury</hi> came away from him to join the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Cornbury</hi> with many other Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, came unto <hi>Exeter,</hi> and attended on his Highneſs, which made all the Army to rejoice. The Prince rode about five Miles out of <hi>Exeter,</hi> to view ſome new Regiments of Horſe which were juſt come into his Service. He gave the Officers and Souldiers a courteous Reception, and made a Speech unto them, upon which the whole Regiments ſhouted, and Huzza'd for Joy. I preached at St. <hi>Carion</hi>'s Church in <hi>Exeter, November</hi> 18.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:49238:32"/> My Text being in <hi>Iſa. 8. 12, 13, 14. Neither fear ye their fear, nor be afraid. Sanctify the Lord of Hoſts him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and let him be your fear, and let him be your dread. And he ſhall be for a Sanctuary.</hi> Now the Church-Wardens of this Pariſh, altho there was no Miniſter to preach, were unwilling to give the Keys (becauſe they were no true Friends of our good Cauſe) inſomuch that I was forc'd to threaten them for their great rudeneſs. The Clerk of the Pariſh going along with me the Day before for the Key, one of the Church-Wardens very rudely broke his Head in ſundry places, for which intolerable Action I immediately had him brought before the Honourable Colonel <hi>Cutts</hi> for this bold Fact, who upon a due ſubmiſſion and acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his Faults, diſmiſſed him with a ſharp Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion: For Modeſty-ſake I conceal his Name, hoping that he's reformed with the Times. The late K. <hi>James</hi> finding his Army begin to moulder away, was very much at a ſtand; however he thought to give us Battel with the remaining part, whereupon he haſten'd to <hi>Sarum</hi> a ſecond time, which we had notice of before we left <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> The Army being now well refreſh'd, and one Man as good as two when we were at <hi>Torbay,</hi> Order was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the Army to march in three Lines: The firſt Line march'd out of the City as far as St. <hi>Mary Ottrie,</hi> and were Quarter'd in and near that Place: The next day the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Line march'd forth of <hi>Exeter</hi> to the ſame place, and the firſt Line advanc'd to <hi>Axminſter:</hi> The third Day the laſt Line march'd, as before, to St. <hi>Mary Ottrie,</hi> the firſt Line advancing ſome to <hi>Beminſter,</hi> and ſome to <hi>Crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn,</hi> the ſecond to <hi>Axminſter</hi> and the adjacent Towns; and the Regiments march'd ſome one Road and ſome another; as the firſt Line advanced, ſo the whole Army moved, which was always according to the Moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our great Maſter: For when he remained any where, then did the whole Army abide in the ſame
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49238:33"/> Quarters. The City of <hi>Exeter</hi> was now freed of all its Souldiers, only the Regiment, of Sir <hi>John Guyes</hi> (which was new raiſed) was order'd to keep this City, and he made Governour thereof. Now many Oxen being brought into this Town to draw the Artillery, and many Horſes being come to carry the Ammunition, and all things neceſſary for War appertaining to our whole Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; We then were ſoon on the March; A Captain with ſome other Officers, and about a hundred Men, came along with it to guard it. Here at <hi>Exeter</hi> was a certain Perſon kept in Cuſtody ſome Days, for ſpeaking very threatning Words againſt his Highneſe the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> but within a while was releaſed. Another was apprehended for a Spy, becauſe he ſaid he had a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the late K. <hi>James</hi> to go into any Mans Houſe, to ſearch for Goods: This Man was alſo accuſed for ſtealing about ten pound from the People of the Houſe where he lodged, but no Money could be found about him, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he alſo was diſmiſſed in few Days. I ſuppoſe our Army was now in Circumference between 20 and 30 Miles. The Prince with all his Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen attending him, rode from <hi>Exeter</hi> unto St. <hi>Mary Ottrie;</hi> the Weather was very Rainy, and the Roads bad for Marching; however we had time enough, for our Stages were not far diſtant one from the other: The places where we Quarter'd were ſcarce able to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us, inſomuch that every Houſe was crowded: Our Van-Guard was advanc'd as faras <hi>Sherborn,</hi> who coming into this Townat at one end, and a party of Horſe (belonging to the late King <hi>James)</hi> coming in at the other, but hearing of our Men, retreated back towards <hi>Sarum:</hi> Our firſt Line being advanced from <hi>Axminſter,</hi> to <hi>Crookhorn</hi> and <hi>Beminſter;</hi> the ſecond to <hi>Axminſter</hi> and <hi>Lime;</hi> and the third Line according to the others Stage before them. Then the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> rode to <hi>Crookhorn</hi> with all his Noble Attendance. The Country People were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:49238:33"/> deſirous to ſee the Prince, and ran in great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers from one Town to another, when they heard for certain which way he came. Here at <hi>Crookhorn</hi> his Highneſe remained the Lord's Day, <hi>Novemb. 25.</hi> And the Gentlemen of the Weſt came and joyn'd him now almoſt at every Stage. On Monday Morning the whole Army March'd; The firſt Line advanced from <hi>Sherborn</hi> to <hi>Wincanton,</hi> the ſecond to <hi>Sherborn,</hi> and the third to <hi>Yet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> with all his Nobles and Gentlemen came to <hi>Sherborn,</hi> and lodged at the Caſtle. The two Armies were near each other by this time, the late King <hi>James</hi> lay at <hi>Salisbury</hi> with his Army, and the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s lay about <hi>Sherborn,</hi> advancing towards him with all poſſible ſpeed. The late King <hi>James</hi> ſeeing his Army moulder thus away, and that Prince <hi>George</hi> was gone to his Brother, with the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> was in ſuch a ſtreight, that he knew not well what to do: And coming to the Market-place at <hi>Sarum,</hi> he made an Oration to the Citizens, telling them that he would ſpend his Blood for the Proteſtant Religion, whenas he had been ſeen at Maſs all the Morning by many of his Auditors; who thereupon derided him in their Hearts. No ſooner had he ended his Speech, but immediately falls to bleeding at his Noſtrils very violently, (as many ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved there-about him) and his Blood could not be ſtopp'd any manner of way. The Citizens hearing the Army of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> was advanced within a few Miles of their City; ſome Perſons coming in at one end of the Town, ſaid they ſaw them not far off: which Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port being noiſed about, ſo Alarm'd the late King <hi>James,</hi> and his Army, That in the midſt of his Bleeding, he commanded his Coach to be made ready, and drive away towards <hi>Windſor</hi> with all poſſible ſpeed, which was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly done. The Foot-Soldiers were ready to deſert the late King, and many did, ſome left their Baggage and Snapſacks behind them; And the Horſe likewiſe being
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:49238:34"/> in ſuch a hurry to get away, that they were ready to ſpoil their Comrades; and the whole Army was in ſuch a confuſed manner, and marched ſo diſorderly, and in ſuch haſte, that the Country ſeeing them, judged they had been routed in a Battel. The late King <hi>James</hi> began to bleed at <hi>Sarum,</hi> and was obſerv'd to continue bleeding ſome days; and coming thus haſtily to <hi>Windſor</hi> the Towns-People that ſaw him, judged that he had been overthrown in Battel: So coming from <hi>Windſor</hi> to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> he turn'd out Sir <hi>Edw. Hales,</hi> who was Governor of the <hi>Tower,</hi> for he had threatned to Bomb this famous Ancient City, and put Mr. <hi>Skelton</hi> his late Ambaſſador in <hi>France,</hi> Governor, who was a Priſoner there but a few days before.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> came and joined the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> at <hi>Sherborn</hi>-Caſtle, upon Thurſday <hi>Novemb. 29.</hi> about four of the Clock in the Afternoon; The Report of which made the Hearts of all the Country People to rejoice, as well as our Army, and many Perſon of Quality flock'd to the Prince to join him. From <hi>Winncanton</hi> the firſt Line of our Army advanced to <hi>Mere,</hi> and the adjacent Towns and Villages; the ſecond Line marched to <hi>Winncanton,</hi> and the third, or laſt, came to <hi>Sherborn.</hi> Now the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with Prince <hi>George</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and very many Lords, Knights, and Gentlemen, came from <hi>Sherborn</hi>-Caſtle unto <hi>Winncan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and quartered there. This was the place where the firſt Skirmiſh paſs'd between the two Armies; the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of which I ſhall impartially relate to the candid and ingenious Reader, as I received an Account thereof from the Miniſter (Mr. <hi>Bulgin)</hi> and from Mr. <hi>VVebb</hi> a Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of Horſe belonging to the late King <hi>James,</hi> who was ſhot there, between his Back-bones and Reins, and lay deſperately ill when we marched by.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:49238:34"/>
            <p>A Lieutenant having his Poſt at this Town, with about four and twenty Souldiers belonging to the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Honourable Major General <hi>Mackay,</hi> hearing that a party of Horſe belonging to the late King <hi>James</hi> were poſting thither, he was ſo magnanimous as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve to fight them; and in order thereto, poſted his Men as ſecurely as he could, in a ſmall Incloſure, at the Eaſt end of the Town, on the left ſide; there was a good Hedg between them and the Road, which was to defend them againſt the Horſe, and through which they were to fire upon the Enemy; but there was a little Gate at one Corner, and a weak dead Hedg. In this Field he poſted moſt of his Men; and on the other ſide the way, juſt oppoſite to this place, he poſted about ſix Souldiers in a little Garden, who had a thick old Hedg to cover them from the Horſe, and through which they were to fire; the Officer himſelf, with four or five Men, keeping the Road: The Enemies Horſe being now advanced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Muſquet-ſhot, the Souldiers would have fired upon them; but the Lieutenant, whoſe name was <hi>Cambel,</hi> not knowing what they might be, whether Friends or Foes, would not permit them, and the more, becauſe a Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Horſe belonging to my Lord <hi>Cornbury</hi> was come in and joined our Forces; and ſo advancing each towards other, our Officer firſt gave them the World, ſaying, <hi>Stand, ſtand, For who are ye?</hi> To which the Enemies Officer, at the Head of the Party of Horſe, anſwered, <hi>I am for King</hi> James, <hi>Who art thou for?</hi> To which our Officer replied, <hi>I am for the Prince of</hi> Orange. <hi>God damn me,</hi> ſays the Enemies Officer, <hi>I will Prince thee.</hi> Whereupon our Officer ſaid, <hi>Fire;</hi> and went bodly up to this Popiſh Officer, and ſhot him in at his Mouth and through the Brains, ſo he drop'd down dead; our Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers firing upon them through the Hedges on each ſide, maul'd them deſperately, and kill'd ſeveral of them. They carried off their Dead preſently, being ten to one:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:49238:35"/>
[for the Enemies Party was about one hundred and fifty, and our Party but five and twenty.] They rode to find out a Place to break in upon our Men; ſo ſome Horſe broke in at the upper end of the Croft, ſome at the lower Corner, and others got in at the little Gate, which, as is ſaid; was open'd by a Towns-man that ſtood near the Place; ſo that our Men charged as faſt as they could to fire upon them, but were now ſurrounded with the Enemy, our Souldiers were divers of them kill'd. They defended themſelves as well as 'twas poſſible for ſuch a handful againſt ſo many; and one or two of them being ſhot in five or ſix places, were offer'd Quarter by the Enemy for their great Courage, but they would not accept of it from the Hands of Papiſts, and therefore choſe rather to die. Now the little Company in the Garden fired di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times, and the Officer, with his Men, kept their Ground awhile, and then got into the Garden to their own Party. The Towns-people were much alarm'd by this Action, and came thronging into the Streets; and kind Providence having ſo ordain'd it, for the ſaving our Men, (elſe, no doubt, they would all have been cut off, being ſo mightily overpowred) that a certain Miller came riding in at the other end of the Town, and hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this Skirmiſh, preſently reported, that he had overtaken a ſtrong Party of Horſe belonging to the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> and that he believed they were now entring the Town: This was brought to the Enemies Ears very quickly, and moreover he call'd to them, and ſaid, <hi>Away, for your Lives, ſave your ſelves, the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies are at hand.</hi> Now theſe Souldiers of the late King <hi>James,</hi> ſeeing the People of the Town ſo thick in the Streets, running here and there, judged that it might be ſo, and hereupon they retreated with all ſpeed, gallop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing away in a confuſed manner; however, they left more behind them kill'd on their ſide, than they had kill'd of our Men; for 'twas the Judgment of all here,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:49238:35"/> that this handful of Souldiers (appertaining to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs the Prince of <hi>Orange)</hi> kill'd more of their Enemies, than they themſelves were in number. There were about fifteen tumbled in one Grave together, and about eight or nine of our Men, the reſt being of the Enemies Party. Our Officers did moſt of them viſit this Mr. <hi>Web,</hi> Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net of Horſe, to hear the manner of this ſmall Action.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Mere</hi> the firſt Line of our Army advanced to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Sarum,</hi> about ſix or ſeven miles; the ſecond Line advanced to <hi>Mere,</hi> and the third to <hi>Wincanton.</hi> All along the Weſt we diſpers'd the Declarations; and where we hapned to quarter on Sunday, we read it there in the Church, as at <hi>Beminſter, Collingburn, Kingston,</hi> and fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other places.</p>
            <p>Near unto <hi>Beminſter</hi> there lived a Gentleman, whoſe Name I ſhall forbear, but a very rigid Papiſt, and one whom I cannot quite forget, becauſe of his unkindneſs, and curſed Intention towards the Army: Hearing that ſome Regiments would paſs that way, he reſolved to give ſome their laſt Meat and Drink, (as his own Neighbours at <hi>Beminſter</hi> informed us when we were there) therefore he cauſed a Beef or two to be kill'd, and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd the Fleſh, making it into Pyes; and poiſon'd alſo a Hogſhead or two of Beer, and as much of Sider, for the <hi>hungry Souldiers</hi> (as he call'd them) againſt they came that way. Some of his Neighbours hearing of this curſed Deſign, ſpread it purpoſely about the Country, to prevent any of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Men from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtroyed; inſomuch that every Regiment was timely warn'd hereof: But as in all great Armies, there will be ſome Straglers, ſo there was ſome in ours, tho not many; and theſe not hearing of this Bait, acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally paſſed that way; and as they approached near the Houſe, they concluded 'twas their beſt courſe to call and drink (there) becauſe it ſhew'd well to the Eye, and People all along were very kind to the Souldiers, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:49238:36"/> would make them drink, and in many Places eat: Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon theſe Straglers went to the Houſe, and asked for ſome Beer; and the People there made them eat and drink freely, ſaying, <hi>Their Maſter had provided for them.</hi> After they had eat and drank, they haſtned towards their Regiments, leſt the Enemies Party ſhould happen to meet them; Being come a little more than a quarter of a mile from the Houſe, they grew ſuddenly ſo weak and faint, that they were not able to go any farther; ſo they lay down under a Tree, not ſuſpecting what was the matter: As they were in this deſperate condition, by meer Providence, there came a Surgeon-Major that way, who eſpying ſome Souldiers (ſuppoſed they were ſome of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Men) he went to ſpeak with them; and ſeeing them look ſo fearfully, (their Eyes being prodigiouſly ſwell'd) he ask'd preſently, What was the matter with them? or, what did ail them? they told him, they knew not, only they had eat and drank at the Gentleman's Houſe behind (point<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Houſe); The Surgeon having heard of their evil Preparations, prepared immediately an Antidote, and gave directions what they muſt do; whereupon they preſently began to vomit, and after ſome time they waxed a little better, and made ſhift to get to the Wag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons which carried ſick Souldiers; and were under the Surgeon-Major's Hands for ſome time. At the very next Town, called <hi>Yetminſter,</hi> one Souldier died in the Night, and none could tell what was the matter with him, being very well when he went to bed, which Souldier I buried there according to our Liturgy: The others that were poiſoned, were ſtrangely altered, their Eyes being ſwell'd after an odd manner.</p>
            <p>Now the Army being advanced near <hi>Sarum;</hi> and the firſt Line being in the City, the ſecond at <hi>Wiltion</hi> and the Towns adjacent, and the Rear Line at <hi>Tevent</hi> and <hi>Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton;</hi> one Line about two or three miles off the City,
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:49238:36"/> and the other about ſeven or eight. The Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range,</hi> with his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Denmark,</hi> his Grace the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> Mareſchal <hi>Schomberg,</hi> Count <hi>Solms,</hi> Count <hi>Naſſau,</hi> Heer <hi>Zuluſtein,</hi> Heer <hi>Benting,</hi> Heer <hi>Overkirk,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Shrewsbury,</hi> Lord Viſcount <hi>Mordant,</hi> the Earl of <hi>Macclesfield,</hi> Lord <hi>Wiltſhire,</hi> Lord <hi>Cornbury,</hi> Lord <hi>Colcheſter,</hi> and ſundry other Lords, Sir <hi>Will. Portman,</hi> Sir <hi>Rowland Gwynn,</hi> Col. <hi>Sidney,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Knights and Gentlemen, rode into the famous City of <hi>Salisbury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The manner of their Entrance into this City, was far more glorious than that of <hi>Exeter;</hi> For here the Mayor and Aldermen met his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> in all their Formalities. Firſt of all marched the Regiment of Foot Guards belonging to Count <hi>Solms,</hi> with their Colours flying, Drums beating, Hoitboys playing; the People thronging in the Street, and making great Accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations. Next, ſome Troops of Horſe, with their Kettle-Drums beating, Colours flouriſhing, Trumpets ſounding, the Officers ſhewing their Courteſy to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple: Then came his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with the Prince of <hi>Denmark</hi> on his right Hand, and the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> on his Left. Never were Windows more crowded with Faces of both Sexes than here; never were Bells ringing more melodiouſly than now at <hi>Sarum;</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were People ſhouting and ecchoing forth <hi>Huzza</hi>'s in the Air more than now. The Biſhop's Palace there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the beſt and moſt meet place, both the Princes rode thither, altho afterwards his Highneſs Prince <hi>George</hi> went to the Quarters aſſign'd him. The Princeſs <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> was gone into the North, with the Ladys, <hi>Churchil</hi> and <hi>Berkley,</hi> and the R. R. Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> to thoſe Forces there in Arms for the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> And hearing that the Army was advanced to <hi>Sarum,</hi> ſhe came unto the City of <hi>Oxford,</hi> where Prince <hi>George</hi> met her Royal Highneſs, and conducted her ſafe to <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:49238:37"/> having a <hi>Dutch</hi> Guard appointed them by the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi> The late King <hi>James</hi>'s Army was now much broken, moſt of the Proteſtant Officers and Souldiers come away, and join'd his Highneſs's Forces. So 'twas apparent to all Men, there would be no Field Battel. Whilſt the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> remained in this City, there was great reſort from all the Country round about to ſee him, who was the Nation's Joy, and the Peoples Delight, becauſe he had done ſo great Things for our Land: And ſuch was his exceeding wiſe Conduct, that the the effuſion of much Blood was prevented.</p>
            <p>After ſome ſtay here, the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> went to <hi>Amsbury,</hi> attended with the Duke of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and many of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nobility and Gentry, beſides <hi>Dutch, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>French:</hi> The firſt Line was advanced towards the moſt renowned City of <hi>London,</hi> a conſiderable way, the Roads here being good for marching: And as the Regiments marched over the Plains, they made pleaſant Figures, ſometimes marching in Battalia, and ſometimes in a Line: The Weather now was very favourable, and the way very good. And being to march near one of the Wonders of the World, called <hi>Stonehenge,</hi> moſt Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments made an halt to view this ſtrange Sight; none that ſaw it could render any ſatisfactory Account concerning it: Certain Officers ask'd the Miniſter of <hi>Amsbury</hi> what was his Opinion, becauſe they preſumed 'twas within the Bounds of his Pariſh; who told them, that he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed it to be a Trophy, or Monument erected in token of ſome notable Victory which was obtain'd there: I muſt confeſs, this is the general Opinion of the greateſt Antiquaries of our Nation.</p>
            <p>The Cuſtom of erecting a <hi>Trophy,</hi> or Monument, in token of Victory is of great Antiquity, and firſt began among the Greeks, who uſed in that place where the Enemies were vanquiſh'd to cut down the Boughs of great Trees, and in the Stocks, or Bodies of them, to hang
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:49238:37"/> up Armour, or other Spoils, taken from the Enemy. Others argued ſtrongly that theſe prodigious Stones were brought out of <hi>Ireland</hi> by <hi>Merlin</hi>'s Magical Art, and ſo curiouſly fram'd and put together. To corroborate this Opinion, they aſſured us, that a piece broken off from theſe Stones, and put into the Wall of any Well, or caſt into the Water, ſhall, for certain, kill and deſtroy all the venemous Creatures therein.</p>
            <p>To proceed, the Army moved daily according to the Motion of his Highneſs, who rode from <hi>Amsbury</hi> unto a certain Gentleman's Houſe near <hi>Collingburn.</hi> The late King <hi>James</hi> being almoſt paſt all hopes, ſent the Marqueſs of <hi>Hallifax,</hi> Earl of <hi>Nottingham,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Godolphin</hi> as Commiſſioners, to treat with the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> immediately; and a Trumpeter was ſent down to know his Highneſs's pleaſure, Whether he would admit of them as ſuch? And his Highneſs was pleaſed to grant them leave. The place appointed them was <hi>Hungerford.</hi> His Highneſs with all his Nobles, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> went to <hi>Littlecott, December 8,</hi> and remain'd there the Morrow, being the Lord's Day [for the Army never march'd on that Day, but once in caſe of Neceſſity, that the Souldiers ſhould not abide about the Forreſt of <hi>Windſor,</hi> becauſe they kill'd the Deer. Hence they march'd from <hi>Barkham</hi> and <hi>Arberſield,</hi> unto <hi>Maidenhead, December</hi> 16, which was the Lord's Day.]</p>
            <p>The firſt Line was now advanced to <hi>Newberry,</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to <hi>Hungerford,</hi> and the Rear Line to <hi>Collingburn, Kingſtone,</hi> and the adjacent Villages; who on Saturday Night <hi>December</hi> 8, received an Alarm (tho it proved a falſe One) ſundry Tradesmen riding home from <hi>Hunger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Market, late in the Evening, were ſeen by ſome of our Scouts, who preſently apprehended them to be a Party of the Enemy's Horſe (being 'twas both late and dark) who thereupon ſpeedily made report unto ſome of the Officers commanding in Chief; inſomuch that the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:49238:38"/> Souldiers were knock'd up in their Quarters to come pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently to their Arms: The Country People were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon in a great fear, not knowing what to do; and this Alarm came from one Regiment to another; for Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Fagell</hi>'s Regiment ſent to advertiſe the Regiment of Colonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> That they might be ready to receive the Enemy. Now they thought this Alarm the rather to be true, becauſe they had heard, That the late King <hi>James</hi>'s Souldiers were reſolv'd to make an Attempt upon thoſe Men with the Artillery and Magazine, That, if poſſible, they might deſtroy our great Guns and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. The Souldiers being thus hurried out of their Beds, ran here and there to ſeek the Enemy: Thus were they marching to and fro the whole Night in the Rain. The Morrow Morning (being the Lord's Day) divers Officers went to ſearch the Woods near to the place where thoſe Tradesmen were firſt ſeen, leſt they ſhould lie in Ambuſh till the Regiments were march'd away, and then attack the Artillery and Magazine-Forces: But none could be found, or heard of thereabout; only they were now inform'd of theſe Tradeſmen, and ſo they return'd to their Regiments.</p>
            <p>The Commiſſioners by this time were come to <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerford;</hi> and theſe following Words, in Writing, were delivered unto the Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
            </p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE King commanded us to acquaint you, That he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth all the Differences and Cauſes of Complaint, (alledged by your Highneſs) ſeem to be referred to a Free Parliament. His Majeſty, as he hath already declared, was reſolv'd before this to call One, but thought that in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent State of Affairs, it was adviſeable to defer it till things were more compos'd. Yet ſeeing that his People ſtill conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued to deſire it, He hath put forth his Proclamation in order to it, and hath iſſued forth his Writs for calling of it.
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:49238:38"/> And to prevent any Cauſe of Interruption in it, he will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to every thing that can be reaſonably required for the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity of all thoſe that ſhall come to it. His Majeſty hath therefore ſent us to attend Your Highneſs for the adjuſting of all Matters that ſhall be agreed to, neceſſary to the Freedom of Elections, and the Security of Sitting, and is ready immediately to enter into a Treaty, in order to it. His Majeſty propoſeth, that in the mean time the reſpective Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies may be reſtrained, within ſuch Limits, and at ſuch a Diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> as may prevent the Apprehenſions that the Parliament may in any kind be diſturbed; being deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous that the Meeting of it may be no longer delay'd, than it muſt be by the uſual and neceſſary Forms.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Hungerford <date>Decemb. 8. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Signed,</hi> 
                        <list>
                           <item>Hallifax, </item>
                           <item>Nottingham, </item>
                           <item>Godolphin.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>His Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> with the advice of his Lords and Gentlemen, in anſwer to the ſame, made theſe Propoſals.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That all Papiſts, and ſuch Perſons as are not quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Law, be diſarmed, disbanded, and removed from all Employments, Civil and Military.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That all Proclamations which reflect upon Us, or any that have come to Us, or declared for Us, be re-called; and that if any Perſons for having ſo aſſiſted, have been committed, that they be forth with ſet at Liberty.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That for the Security and Safety of the City of <hi>London,</hi> the Cuſtody and Government of the <hi>Tower</hi> be immediately put into the Hands of the ſaid City.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That if his Majeſty ſhall think fit to be at <hi>London,</hi> during the ſitting of the Parliament, that We may be there alſo, with equal Number of our Guards. Or if his Majeſty ſhall pleaſe to be in any place from <hi>London,</hi> at whatever diſtance he thinks fit, that we may be at a place of the ſame diſtance. And that the Reſpective Armies
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:49238:39"/> do remove from <hi>London</hi> Thirty Miles, and that no more Foreign Forces be brought into the Kingdom.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. That for the Security of the City of <hi>London,</hi> and their Trade, <hi>Tilbury-Fort</hi> be put into the Hands of the ſaid City.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. That to prevent the Landing of <hi>French,</hi> or other Foreign Troops, <hi>Portſmouth</hi> may be put into ſuch Hands, as by your Majeſty and Us ſhall be agreed upon.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. That ſome ſufficient part of the Publick Revenue be aſſigned Us, for the Maintaining of our Forces, until the Meeting of a Parliament.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Given at <hi>Littlecot,</hi> 
                        <date>Decemb. 9. 1688.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>W. H.</hi> Prince of <hi>Orange.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>The late King <hi>James</hi> perceiving now that he was in an evil Caſe, in relation to ſundry Matters, thought it high time to ſecure himſelf, whereupon <hi>December</hi> 10, he wrote a Letter to the Earl of <hi>Feverſham,</hi> now at the Head of his Army, ſignifying his Intention therein. And on the Morrow Morning, <hi>December</hi> 11, he withdrew himſelf in order to his departure out of the Kingdom, and being on his Journey near <hi>Feverſham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> was taken in a Diſguiſe and ſent back to <hi>London.</hi> The Earl of <hi>Fever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> having read the Contents of the late K. <hi>James</hi> his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, ſent another ſpeedily for to advertiſe his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> that his late Majeſty was gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way: And that for his own part He would make no Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition againſt any, and ſo prevent the Effuſion of Blood. The news of the late King <hi>James</hi> being gone away, flew like lightening from <hi>Eaſt</hi> to <hi>Weſt,</hi> and from <hi>North</hi> to <hi>South.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our Army was now advanc'd far towards the City of <hi>London,</hi> The firſt line being March'd from <hi>Newberry</hi> to <hi>Reading, Tylehurſtone,</hi> and the adjacent places: The ſecond line advanc'd to <hi>Newberry,</hi> and the third line to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:49238:39"/> 
               <hi>Hungerford.</hi> The Prince rode to <hi>Henly,</hi> attended with his Nobility and Gentry; ſundry Regiments of the firſt and ſecond Line being marched thither, and the Rear Line was come to <hi>Newberry:</hi> Here we received the firſt poſitive News of the late King <hi>James</hi> being gone away, As ſoon as it was certainly known about the City of, <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> that the late King was withdrawn, in order to his departure out of the Kingdom, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal aſſembled at <hi>Guildhal, Decemb.</hi> 11. and there agreed upon, and ſigned a Declaration, Entituled, <hi>The Declaration of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal in and about the Cities of</hi> London <hi>and</hi> Weſtminſter, <hi>aſſembled at</hi> Guildhal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> The ſubſtance of which being to ſhew, that the late King <hi>James</hi> was gone away, and to declare that they would aſſiſt his Highneſs with their uttermoſt Endeavours in the obtaining a Free Parliament with all ſpeed, and in preſerving, as much as in them lay, the Peace and Security of the Cities of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter;</hi> by taking care to diſarm all Papiſts, and ſecure all Jeſuits and Romiſh Prieſts, and in all things endeavour to promote his Highneſs's generous Intentions. This Declaration they ordered to be preſented to his Highneſs, by the Earl of <hi>Pembrook,</hi> the Lord Viſcount <hi>Weymouth,</hi> the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Ely,</hi> the Lord <hi>Culpeper.</hi> The ſame Day the Lieutenancy of the City of <hi>London</hi> met there alſo, and agreed upon, and ſigned an humble Addreſs to be preſented to his Highneſs by a Committee appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, <hi>viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Clayton,</hi> Sir <hi>William Ruſſel,</hi> Sir <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſil Firebraſs,</hi> Kts. and <hi>Charles Duncome</hi> Eſq.</p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of which Addreſs was, to acknowledg the great Danger his Illuſtrious Highneſs had expos'd himſelf to, both by Sea and land, for the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion, and the Laws and Liberties of this Kingdom, and the happy Relief he had brought to us; and therefore they humbly deſired that his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs would be pleaſed to repair unto the City of <hi>London,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:49238:40"/> with all the convenient ſpeed he could, for perfecting the great Work He had ſo happily begun, to the general Joy and Satisfaction of all. The ſame day the Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Commons of the City of <hi>London,</hi> in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Council aſſembled, agreed on and ſigned an Addreſs to be preſented to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> the Contents whereof was, To acknowledg the peril his Highneſs had expoſed himſelf to, both by Sea and Land, and the happy Deliverance he had brought to our Nation; and therefore they, in the name of their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital City, did implore his Highneſs's Protection, and did humbly beſeech his Highneſs to vouchſafe to repair to the City, where his Highneſs ſhould be received with univerſal Joy and Satisfaction. All which Addreſſes were preſented to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> by the Perſons appointed, the <hi>14th</hi> of <hi>December,</hi> at <hi>Henly;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accompanied with a great number of Citizens, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But whilſt all this was tranſacting, the late King was ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed at <hi>Feverſham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> in a ſmall Veſſel; his Guards and Coach was ſent for him, and he returned to <hi>White<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hal,</hi> Sunday, <hi>Dec.</hi> 16. about ſix of the Clock in the Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoon, which was ſome ſurpriſe to the Prince of <hi>Orange;</hi> however he purſued his Journey to <hi>London,</hi> and from <hi>Henley</hi> went to <hi>Windſor,</hi> and ſet up his Standard; where we ſhall humbly crave the liberty to leave his Highneſs at this famous Caſtle, with all the Nobility and Gentry attending him, and proceed with his Highneſs's Puiſſant Army for a while.</p>
            <p>The Rear Regiments coming up, ſome were quartered in one Village, and ſome in another; at <hi>Tylehurſton</hi> the Regiment of the Right Honourable Colonel <hi>Sidney,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded by the Honourable Colonel <hi>Cutts,</hi> was now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm'd, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> were coming, and had burnt <hi>Kingston</hi> upon <hi>Thames,</hi> putting Man, Woman, and Child to the Sword; and that part of theſe Tories were gone unto <hi>Baſing-ſtoke</hi> to do the fame there; inſomuch
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:49238:40"/> that a certain Perſon who was an Inhabitant of that Town, was conſtrained to keep away from the Place, and come to the Regiments. There was now riding and poſting from one Town to another all the Night long, and People every where in a kind of confuſion. As part of our Regiments of Horſe were coming to <hi>Reading,</hi> the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Souldiers gave out great ſwelling Words, and lofty Speeehes, how they would hack them to pieces there, and how they would defend the ſeven Bridges; This was on the Lord's Day, (and as we were informed there, by divers Perſons of Credit, they deſigned to maſſacre the People at their Worſhip, had they not been prevented) which obliged the Inhabitants to ſend to the advanc'd part of the Prince's Army, then a few miles di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, who readily came to their Aſſiſtance, being con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted a by-way into the Town, and fought ſo coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>that in a few minutes they put the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to flight, took ſome, and kill'd about 20 upon the place, with the loſs only of the Officer that led them, and the Guide that conducted them into the Town.</p>
            <p>At <hi>Maidenhead</hi> there was ſuch another Action perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> (as we heard there from a Worthy Divine); The <hi>Iriſh</hi> perceiving the Army of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> advanced ſo faſt, and with ſuch ſpeed towards <hi>London,</hi> perſwaded the late King <hi>James</hi> to fortify <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhead-Bridg,</hi> it being the ready Road, and a difficult Poſt to be taken. Therefore in a new Brick Houſe which is built between the Bridg and Town, they made ſundry Port-holes for their great Guns, and put new Pales to blind them, and ſundry places above to ſhoot with Muſquets: And on the middle of the Bridg, they plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a great Gun or two, and here they were reſolved to maul the Prince's Army, as they ſaid. Indeed, thoſe that underſtand Fortification well, have preſumed, that the Paſſage there might be ſo fortified, that thouſands of Men ſhould not win it, becauſe the Water ran in the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:49238:41"/> Road-way a conſiderable length, or ſome hundred Yards; and the Bridg is ſo narrow, that a Man can hardly go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long without falling, except he hold by the Rails; the Water too being up to a Man's middle here in the Road at the loweſt Ebb: So the <hi>Iriſh</hi> bravadoing here at this Poſt, what they would do, certain worthy Perſons there conſulted together how to diſperſe the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> or cauſe them to go away, for they perceived well the Hearts of all Proteſtants were ſet upon his Highneſs, their Deliverer, under God, and by his Bleſſing; and the End of their Conſultation was this: Sundry Perſons of Courage and Reſolution ſhould go in the Dark, about Midnight, having each of them an old Barrel, or an old Kettle, ſtanding at a certain equal diſtance from each other, they ſhould beat the <hi>Dutch</hi> March: Which Stratagem took goodeffect, for theſe Men being got within a ſmall diſtance of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> began to beat a <hi>Dutch</hi> March; they no ſooner heard it, but were prodigiouſly ſurprized, crying, <hi>Hark, Hark;</hi> and another preſently made anſwer, <hi>God damn my Blood if it be not the</hi> Dutch <hi>come upon us;</hi> and forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they began to run and haſten away, without mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their great Guns, or taking away any thing; nay, happy was that Man that could get before his Comrade; and whither they went, no Man could tell. So the Souldiers belonging to his Highneſs, coming to <hi>Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head,</hi> hearing of this Exploit, highly commended both the Contrivers and Actors in it, brought away the Guns, and all that was left, to <hi>Windſor</hi>-Caſtle. And ſo I have done with both the Armies; in relation to Skir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhes or Actions.</p>
            <p>His Highneſs being now at <hi>Windſor,</hi> with all his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility and Gentry about him, the Citizens of <hi>London</hi> flock'd mightily to viſit Him, and congratulate his ſafe Arrival ſo far.</p>
            <p>The Army being now all about <hi>Windſor,</hi> and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jacent Towns and Villages, the Souldiers, through the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:49238:41"/> perſwaſions of the Country People; kill'd and deſtroy'd hundreds of Deer in the Foreſt; and hundreds more had been deſtroy'd, if ſo be his Highneſs had not given out his Royal Order to the contrary.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Iriſh</hi> Tories much abuſed the worthy Miniſter of <hi>Tylehurſton,</hi> ſtripping his Rings off his Fingers, with the Skin and Fleſh; threatning his Wife in Bed; and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly had murder'd the whole Family, if ſo be the Maid had not leap'd out of a Window, and call'd the Neighbours ſpeedily to aſſiſt them, for they broke open the Door with on Iron made for the ſame purpoſe, which they forgot and left behind them, with their Dark Lanthorn, both which I ſaw, They ſwore di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers times by St. <hi>Patrick,</hi> they would cut them all into pieces, if they would not give them Mony, for they muſt ſhortly be gone, and the late King had not paid them: So hearing the Neighbours coming, they took their Horſes and rode away, having above thirty Pounds in Mony, Plate, and Rings, for they took the old Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>womans Rings off her Fingers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>December</hi> the <hi>18th,</hi> his Highneſs parted from <hi>Windſor,</hi> dined at <hi>Sion</hi>-Houſe, and came that Evening to St. <hi>James's,</hi> amidſt the loud Acclamations of a vaſt number of People of all Sorts and Ranks, the Bells every-where ringing; the Evening concluded with vaſt Bonſires, and ſuch general Joy as can ſcarce be parallel'd.</p>
            <p>The next day the late King <hi>James</hi> (ſeeing the Scene of Affairs altered) parted from <hi>Whitehal,</hi> went down the River to <hi>Rocheſter,</hi> and from thence took Shipping for <hi>Breſt,</hi> whither the Queen, and ſuppoſed Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> was gone before, and himſelf ſoon after, where I'le leave him.</p>
            <p>Moſt of the Nobility congratulated his Highneſs's ſafe arrival at St, <hi>James's;</hi> and on the <hi>20th</hi> the Aldermen and Common Couucil of the City of <hi>London,</hi> attended his Highneſs upon the ſame account; and the Lord Mayor
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:49238:42"/> being diſabled by Sickneſs, Sir <hi>George Treby</hi> Kt. Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Honourable City of <hi>London,</hi> made an Oration to his Highneſs, to this effect;</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Great Sir,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WHen we look back to the laſt Month, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template the ſwiftneſs and fulneſs of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Deliverance, aſtoniſh'd, we think it miraculous. Your Highneſs led by the Hand of Heaven, and call'd by the Voice of the People, has preſerved our deareſt Intereſt, the Proteſtant Religion, which is Primitive Chriſtianity reſtored. Our Laws, which are our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Title to our Lives, Liberties and Eſtates, and without which this World were a Wilderneſs. But what Retribution can we make to your Highneſs? Our Thoughts are full charged with Gratitude. Your Highneſs has a laſting Monument in the Hearts, in the Prayers, in the Praiſes of all good Men amongſt us. And late Poſterity will celebrate your ever-glorious Name, till Time ſhall be no more.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>December</hi> the <hi>25th,</hi> the Lords Spiritual and Temporal asſſembled at the Houſe of Lords, <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and there ageeed upon, and ſigned an Addreſs, wherein they hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſired his Highneſs in this Conjuncture, to take upon him the Adminiſtration of Publick Affairs, both Civil and Military, and the Diſpoſal of the Publick Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venue, for the preſervation of our Religion, Rights, Laws, Liberties, and Properties, and of the Peace of the Nation; and that his Highneſs would take into his Care, the Condition of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and endeavour, by the moſt ſpeedy and effectual Means, to prevent the Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers threatning that Kingdom. All which the Lords Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual and Temporal make their Requeſts to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, to undertake and exerciſe till the Meeting of the intended Convention, <hi>Jan,</hi> 22. next.</p>
            <pb n="73" facs="tcp:49238:42"/>
            <p>Moreover, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> in this Extraordinary Conjuncture, did humbly deſire his Highneſs to cauſe Letters to be written, ſubſcribed by Himſelf, to the Lords Spiritual and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, being Proteſtants, and to the ſeveral Counties, Univerſities, Cities, Boroughs, and Cinque-Ports of <hi>England, Wales</hi> and Town of <hi>Berwick</hi> Upon <hi>Tweed;</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining Directions for the chooſing in all ſuch Counties, Cities, Univerſities, Boroughs, and Cinque-Ports, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Ten days after the receipt of the ſaid reſpective Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſuch a number of Perſons to repreſent them, as are of right to be ſent to Parliament; And the Perſons ſo choſen, to Meet and Sit at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> on the Two and Twentieth day of <hi>January:</hi> Both which were ſigned by all the Lords Spiritual and Temporal then Aſſembled, and preſented to his Highneſs the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> the ſame day at St <hi>James</hi>'s. All which his Highneſs was pleaſed to Do according to their Deſires.</p>
            <p>Now the Lords and Commons being Met at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the Two and Twentieth of <hi>January</hi> 1688, According to the Direction of his Highneſs's Letters, They agreed upon and Ordered, That the Thanks of both Houſes ſhould be returned to his Highneſs in the behalf of the whole Nation, for his Highneſs happy Deliverance of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from Popery, Slavery, and Deſpotick Power; and for the Preſervation of the Proteſtant Religion and the Laws, Rights, Priviledges, and Cuſtoms of our Land, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And moreover to beſeech his Highneſs to continue the Adminiſtration of publick Affairs Civil and Milita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and the Diſpoſal of the publick Revenue, until ſuch time as farther Application be made to his Highneſs: All which his Highneſs was pleaſed to do and exerciſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſire. And with all expedition on the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> the Lords and Commons conſulted a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Settlement of our Government: And agreed that the late King <hi>James</hi> the Second having endeavour'd
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:49238:43"/> to ſubvert and extirpate the Proteſtant Religion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and having abdicated the Government, the Throne was thereby become Vacant, They did reſolve that <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> be, and be decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red King and Queen of <hi>England France</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the <hi>12th</hi> of <hi>February,</hi> Her Royal Highneſs the Princeſs of <hi>Orange</hi> arrived at <hi>Whitehall,</hi> the welcome news whereof was received with Ringing of Bells, Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, and other publick Demonſtrations of Joy. The next day the Lords and Commons aſſembled at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> attended their Highneſſes at the Banqueting-houſe with their Reſolve, and received their Conſent thereto, and about 11 of the Clock proclaimed <hi>William</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange,</hi> King and Queen of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the Dominions thereunto belonging. After that their Majeſties were Proclaim'd before <hi>Whitehall;</hi> And the Lord Mayor and Aldermen of the Famous City of <hi>London,</hi> together with the Sheriffs met the Lords and Heralds at Arms at <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> and there Proclaimed their Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,&amp;c.</hi> And ſo proceeded to the Royal <hi>Exchange,</hi> where the ſame was done a third time.</p>
            <p>The day concluding with Ringing of Bells and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fires, to the General Satisfaction of all.</p>
            <p>After their moſt excellent Majeſties were proclaimed all over <hi>England,</hi> there was great preparation made in order to their Majeſties Coronation: The Day being come, <hi>viz. April 11,</hi> 1689. Their Majeſties came from <hi>Whitehall</hi> to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> and the Nobility being put in Order by the Heralds, They came down in State into <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall,</hi> where the Swords and Spurs were preſented to them. Their Majeſties being at <hi>Weſtminſter-Abby,</hi> the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> preached the Sermon, his Text being <hi>2 Sam.</hi> 23, 3, 4. And after the Ceremonies of the Coro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:49238:43"/> were finiſhed, about four of the Clock the Crowns were put upon their Royal Heads by the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> aſſiſted by ſeveral other Biſhops. At the ſight whereof the People ſhouted, the Drums and Trumpets ſounded, the great Guns at the Tower, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were diſcharged, and the Peers and Peereſſes put on their Coronets.</p>
            <p>Their Majeſties being Crowned, returned to <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Hall,</hi> And Dinner being ended, and the whole Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity perform'd with great Splendour and Magnificence, about Eight in the evening their Majeſties return'd to <hi>White-Hall.</hi> Where I moſt humbly leave them, hearti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſeeching Almighty God to bleſs and preſerve their moſt excellent Majeſties, that they may long Live and Flouriſh together, To the advancement of his Glory, the Good of his Church, the Safety, Honour and Welfare of their Majeſties Kingdoms, and the exceeding Joy and Comfort of all Good Proteſtants. As for all their Enemies let then (O God) be daily diſcover'd and brought to Shame and Confuſion; But upon their Sacred and Royal Heads, let the Crowns of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> long Flouriſh.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
